<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The compleat troller, or, The art of trolling with a description of all the utensils, instruments, tackling, and materials requisite thereto, with rules and directions how to use them : as also a brief account of most of the principal rivers in England / by a lover of the sport.</title>
            <author>Nobbes, Robert, 1652-1706?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27439</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13156289</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199384</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240898313</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1193</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13156289</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The compleat troller, or, The art of trolling with a description of all the utensils, instruments, tackling, and materials requisite thereto, with rules and directions how to use them : as also a brief account of most of the principal rivers in England / by a lover of the sport.</title>
                  <author>Nobbes, Robert, 1652-1706?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. James for Tho. Helder ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Ro. Nobbes.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Fishing --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Trolling (Fishing) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Rivers --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:2"/>
            <p>THE Compleat Troller, OR, THE ART OF TROLLING.</p>
            <p>WITH A Description of all the Utensils, Instruments, Tackling, and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials requisite thereto: With Rules and Directions how to use them.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO A Brief Account of most of the Principal RIVERS in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of the Sport.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>— Trahit sua quem{que} voluptas.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. James</hi> for <hi>Tho. Helder</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Worshipful JAMES TRYON ESQUIRE, OF <hi>Bullwick</hi> in <hi>Northamptonshire;</hi> A Favourer of this ART. The Author wisheth all Health and Honour here, and Happiness hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TIs both my duty and my debt, to return the improvement of my talent to you, from whom I first received it, and to pay my thanks for those borrowed sparks which have since kindled and increased into a flame. That debtor is too ungrateful, and deserves to have no favour shew'd him in the principal, that never comes to pay, much less acknowledge an interest. This Obligation, Sir, was one Motive to address this Piece to you, having at first been initiated in this little Art I pretend to, by your Brother and your self; but fearing withal the severe and critical cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of a more judicious Eye. Be pleased there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:199384:4"/> to accept of this small Tribute, not for any worth or desert of its own, but as a Token of my Gratitude. Yuor Name (I confess) is too Great to stand in the Front of so inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a <hi>Paper</hi> as this, wherewith I here present you, and might make a suitable Frontispiece for some for more excellent Work. Whatever it be, it begs your Candid Acceptance; it may parhaps need, but I fear it deserves not so good a Patron. Another reason (Sir) why I offer this Tract to you, is an Ambition I have to bring the World better acquainted with so great a part of its own Treasure, and to make it know that there are yet some such worthy Persons as your Self, whom even they that are Enemies to this present World, cannot refuse both to love and honour. I shall forbear at this time to display your Merits, in reference to my own particular; least he that reads this and sees Your Name praefixed, may expect more by the Epistle than is performed in the Book. And so I make my self Guilty of his Pride and Indiscretion, that sets a fair Porch before a sorry Building. This only Sir, I shall endeavour, and do beg You to believe, that I shall always be industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to manifest my self,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Worshipful,</salute>
               <signed>Yours in all Christian Services, <hi>RO. NOBBES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Ingenious Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not any desire either of profit or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that induc'd me to write this Piece, but only the solicitations of some private Friends, concurring with my own Nature and Inclination, which was always addicted to this Sport, I never could see any thing of this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in particular: <hi>The Compleat Angler</hi> hints the most at it, as first of the Nature and Generation, and Age of a <hi>Pike,</hi> quoting the same Author <hi>Gesner</hi> that I do. He also observes some Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Effects of him, the Spawning time, all sorts of Baits; especially of the Frog, he speaks much, and the Ledger Bait. He hath inserted a Story of the Antipathy between a Land Frog, which he conceives venemous, and a Pike in a Pond in <hi>Bohemia.</hi> He shews the way to bait the Hook, as also to play it with Bladders, Bullrushes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Teaches a way to charm and invite the fish, by sweetning the Bait with Gum of Ivy dissolved in Oil of Spike; as likewise a Receipt to roast a Pike. This is the sum of Mr. <hi>Walton</hi>'s Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course. Then there is the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s <hi>Recra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:5"/> hath one Chapter, but much the same as the other, as borrowed from him. I never could see any other concerning <hi>Trolling,</hi> though if there be, it may be of an old standing; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing new does more please, because <hi>Men hominum est noritatis avida.</hi> I have not put it in that florid Dress of Eloquence or Rhetorical Phrases, nor indeed would the Subject bear it.</p>
            <q>
               <lg xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ornari res ipsa negat, contenta doceri.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg xml:lang="eng">
                  <l>The thing itself is only well content,</l>
                  <l>To be for use, and not for Ornament.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>I confess I have not had that Experience in the Art, which many have that have made it their business for the space of several years; and I but a late pretender; however this may invite some that are more judicious and able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Work; in the mean time use this till a better comes, and think of that of the Poet,
<q>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>— <hi>Si quid novisti rectius istis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Candidus imperti, si non his utere mecum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="eng">
                     <l>If any thing thou know'st that better is,</l>
                     <l>Impart it, else content thy self with this.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be expected that this Discourse should have increased into any larger Volume,
<pb facs="tcp:199384:5"/> these being only the private Sentiments and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of my own Experience. The first Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is always the least, if it were worthy of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Impression, it might receive some Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as having the advantage of being enlarged by the help of some new and more refined Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Nor is the subject Matter enough copious to make a fuller Treatise, it being confin'd to one particular manner of Fishing; which if it had extended to the generality of the Art, and to all the Fresh Water Inhabitants, it might have made this diminutive piece to swell into a Folio.</p>
            <p>The Design of it is only to give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m some insight and instructions, that are wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but desire to learn: not that it can benefit those that are already taught, and perhaps may find, or at least pretend to find many errors in it; for this I can attest, that what is said is as true as <hi>Probatum est;</hi> having not confided to any mans judgment but to my own experience. Whether then it be approved on or not, it must take its fortune as all other Books do, which are blamed by some and commended by others:
<q>
                  <lg xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>
                        <hi>— Habent sua fata libelli —</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:lang="eng">
                     <l>— The Poet sings</l>
                     <l>Books have their chance as well as other things.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As plain as it is, it may be serviceable to some, and if it had been far better and more accurately
<pb facs="tcp:199384:6"/> done, it might have been condemned by others. Every man that is a Fisherman hath some private thoughts of his own, which he will still prefer before others. Besides the Diversions of Fishing are now generally undervalued, it being an Art which few take pleasure in; nothing passing for noble and delightful, which is not brave and cost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as though men could not gratifie their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses without the consumption of their Estates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hawking</hi> and <hi>Hunting</hi> have had their Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies celebrated with large Encomiums, and though I design not to slight or disparage those Noble Recreations, which have been so much famed in all Ages and by all degrees, yet this I must affirm, that they fall not within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass of every mean person to pursue, being as it were only entailed on vast estates; for if lower Fortunes should seek to enjoy them, <hi>Actaeon</hi>'s Fable might prove a true Story, and these Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Birds make a prey upon their Masters. Besides those Recreations are more obnoxious to Choller and Passion than these of ours. Our simple Art composes the Soul to that quiet and serenity, which gives a man the fullest possession and fruition of himself and all his enjoyments.</p>
            <p>This clearness and equanimity of Spirit being a matter of so high a concern, is of much value and esteem in the opinion of many profound Philosophers. Witness that Excellent Tract of <hi>Petrarche, De Tranquilitate Animo,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb facs="tcp:199384:6"/> he that lives, <hi>Sibi &amp; Deo,</hi> leads the most Happy Life. Though all these Contentments and many more, both for Health and Pleasure, as well to gratifie the Senses as delight the Mind, do arise from this cheap, and as some call it, mean Melancholy Art: I say though all these satisfactions do procced from it, and it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds pleasure at such an easie rate, yet I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to meet with no other Entertainment in the publishing of it, then neglect, if not scorn, contempt, and neglect. Some few there are that have cast off their other Recreations and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this; though I never knew any repent of their learning this, and with-draw their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from their beloved Recreation. If this Art therefore may prove a noble rest to thy mind, it will be a great satisfaction to his, who is thy Well-wishing Friend and Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:7"/>
            <head>To his Ingenious Friend Mr. <hi>ROBERT NOBBES,</hi> On his Book called <hi>The Compleat Troller.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>GO on <hi>(Dear Brother)</hi> to display thine Art,</l>
            <l>Of thy Experience lend the World a part:</l>
            <l>Let thy Light shine, that Men may see thereby</l>
            <l>There's nothing private kept can edify.</l>
            <l>Hide not thy Talent: Dread that cursed fate</l>
            <l>Of him that hid it; and communicate.</l>
            <l>Blush not, nor fear thy secrets to unfold;</l>
            <l>For what thou say'st has been approved of old,</l>
            <l>And practis'd too; the difference only this,</l>
            <l>Their sport in salt, thine in fresh water is;</l>
            <l>The good Disciples first catch'd fish; and then</l>
            <l>They left their Nets, and afterwords catch'd Men.</l>
            <l>From which we may this Observation make,</l>
            <l>'Tis lawful Fish as well as Men to take,</l>
            <l>Thy Sacred Function is Divine, and all</l>
            <l>Thy Recreations Apostolical.</l>
            <l>Catch what thou long hast fish'd for, then go pray,</l>
            <l>Catch one great Fish, and throw thy Net away.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your truly humble Servant,</hi> G. D. <hi>of</hi> Trin. Coll.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:7"/>
            <head>To his Esteemed Friend Mr. <hi>ROBERT NOBBES,</hi> On his Book of TROLLING.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LEt proud <hi>Actaeon</hi> chase the tim'rous hart,</l>
               <l>And fair <hi>Diana</hi> pierce him with a Dart.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Pan</hi> the Satyrs and the Nymphs controll,</l>
               <l>And briny <hi>Nereus</hi> on the Billows roll.</l>
               <l>Whil'st thou the Brooks and silver streams do'st greet,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Avon, Cham, Welland,</hi> and <hi>Nine,</hi> that meet.</l>
               <l>Thou do'st not treat of that deformed Race,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Neptune</hi> governs with his Triple Mace:</l>
               <l>Not of that Monster in the Ocean deep,</l>
               <l>Which did in's Belly three days <hi>Jonas</hi> keep:</l>
               <l>Nor of the <hi>Orke</hi> that on <hi>Caephean</hi> Strand,</l>
               <l>Bold <hi>Perseus</hi> slew with strong and mighty hand.</l>
               <l>Nor of th' Admirer of sweet Harp, that bore</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arion</hi> safely on his back to th' Shore.</l>
               <l>Nor of that Fish that bears a Sword in's Snout,</l>
               <l>Nor the fierce Thrasher, that does fling about.</l>
               <l>Nor th' Crocodile, that weeps when he does wrong;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he Turbat, Sturgeon, or the Conger long.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hese are the Flock of <hi>Proteus</hi> Watry Fold,</l>
               <l>And are too strong for slender Lines to hold.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hy Reoreation hath more easie been,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n Rivers fresh, adorn'd with Meadows green.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:8"/>
               <l>Checker'd with Flowers, cloath'd in <hi>Ver</hi>'s Livery,</l>
               <l>Enamell'd round with <hi>Flora</hi>'s Tapestry.</l>
               <l>These are thy Countrey pastimes and delights,</l>
               <l>Proud of good luck, when greedy <hi>Lupus</hi> bites,</l>
               <l>And cross the stream thy slender line does draw,</l>
               <l>Gorging thy glistering bait in's hungry Maw;</l>
               <l>Then strike him gently, tire him, and lie down;</l>
               <l>Take him by th' Eyes, and give him leave to drown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In these Diversions thou do'st imitate</l>
               <l>Those Twelve Christ chose his Word to propogate,</l>
               <l>This Recreation they did countenance,</l>
               <l>And by their practice did it much advance,</l>
               <l>Thou their Example hast before thine Eyes,</l>
               <l>How they did use this harmless Exercise;</l>
               <l>In this thou truly do'st Apostolize.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>R. L. Mr.</hi> of <hi>Arts.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:8"/>
            <head>ON THE <hi>Antiquity and Invention</hi> OF FISHING, And its Praise in general.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen God at first plac'd <hi>Adam</hi> in a Seat</l>
               <l>So rare, so rich, so princely, and so great,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Edens</hi> fair Garden Eastward to the Sun,</l>
               <l>Thro whose fat soil four silver streams did run.</l>
               <l>The first <hi>Euphrates,</hi> whose fair waves do kiss</l>
               <l>The Monarchs Towers of proud <hi>Semiramis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swift <hi>Pison</hi> thence, and <hi>Gihon</hi> did arise, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tigris</hi> the Fourth to water <hi>Paradise;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>These in their kind were furnished to present</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> with Fish from th'Watry Element:</l>
               <l>This added to his bliss, by which we see</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fishing</hi> derives an ancient Pedigree,</l>
               <l>And bears its date from the Forbidden Tree.</l>
               <l>Next unto him that built the Wooden Wall,</l>
               <l>But for whose Ark the Flood had drowned all.</l>
               <l>Yet still the <hi>Fish</hi> mov'd in their proper Sphere,</l>
               <l>They neither Rain, nor Deluge deep did fear.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:9"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> with them himself might recreate, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 8.</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Dove</hi> brought news the Waters did abate.</l>
               <l>Food sure was scarce, when Mr. <hi>Flood</hi> had left,</l>
               <l>Few Beasts but those for procreation kept.</l>
               <l>Hunger might force eight persons to devise</l>
               <l>A trick to take what <hi>Fish</hi> to th' top did rise.</l>
               <l>Now this to Poets fiction did afford</l>
               <l>How th' empty World should be with people stor'd.</l>
               <l>When good <hi>Deucalion</hi> and his <hi>Pyrrha</hi> dear,</l>
               <l>Were left of all that overwhelmed were.</l>
               <l>They to an ancient Temple went, that stood</l>
               <l>Forlorn and wasted by the raging Flood.</l>
               <l>Prostrate they fell upon the sacred ground,</l>
               <l>Devoutly praying th' Earth might re-abound.</l>
               <l>The Goddess heard their prayers, &amp; bid them take</l>
               <l>Their Mothers bones, &amp; throw behind their back.</l>
               <l>This Oracle obscure and dark of sense,</l>
               <l>Amaz'd their minds, what they might draw from thence.</l>
               <l>They then view'd hill and dale, each rock &amp; tree,</l>
               <l>And thought the <hi>Earth</hi> their <hi>Mother</hi> well might be.</l>
               <l>Therefore to try if it were false or true,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The scatter'd stones</hi> behind their <hi>backs</hi> they threw,</l>
               <l>Forthwith the <hi>stones</hi> as they had <hi>life</hi> conceiv'd,</l>
               <l>Began to move, and more and more receiv'd</l>
               <l>The shape of <hi>Man.</hi> Thus was the <hi>World</hi> again</l>
               <l>Supply'd with <hi>people</hi> sprung with little <hi>pain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But yet no <hi>Birds</hi> or <hi>Beasts</hi> for <hi>meat</hi> was found,</l>
               <l>Since the great <hi>Deluge</hi> all destroy'd and drown'd.</l>
               <l>Then did <hi>Deucalion</hi> first the <hi>Art</hi> invent</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Fishing,</hi> and to <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> he went:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:9"/>
               <l>There from the <hi>Trees long rinds &amp; crooks he brake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And made them <hi>hooks</hi> and <hi>lines</hi> the <hi>Fish</hi> to take.</l>
               <l>In this rude sort began this simple <hi>Art,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Fish</hi> as yet had felt but little smart.</l>
               <l>And were to bite more eager, apt, and bold,</l>
               <l>In that first Age, which was then all of Gold.</l>
               <l>But when in time the fear and dread of <hi>Man</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fell more and more on th' <hi>Creatures,</hi> they began</l>
               <l>To stand in awe of this Usurping <hi>King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That did both <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> in thraldom bring.</l>
               <l>'Twas then a <hi>Work</hi> of greater skill to take</l>
               <l>The wary <hi>Fish</hi> in any <hi>Pond</hi> or <hi>Lake.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So worse and worse two <hi>Ages</hi> more did pass,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hooks</hi> were made of <hi>Silver</hi> and of <hi>Brass;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>Hemp</hi> and <hi>Flax</hi> were framed new,</l>
               <l>So still this <hi>Art</hi> more perfect daily grew.</l>
               <l>But at the last the <hi>Iron Age</hi> grew near,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hooks</hi> of hardest <hi>Steel</hi> invented were:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rods</hi> of lightest <hi>Cane</hi> and <hi>Hazel Plant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Hair</hi> no <hi>Skill</hi> did want.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus far the <hi>Fable.</hi> —next the <hi>Truth</hi> presents</l>
               <l>How <hi>Fish</hi> of <hi>wonders</hi> have been <hi>instruments.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>monstrous Fish God</hi> did prepare, to save (<hi>Jon.</hi> 1.</l>
               <l>The angry <hi>Prophet</hi> in the <hi>Euxine</hi> Wave.</l>
               <l>Which doth for us an <hi>Observation</hi> make,</l>
               <l>That to a <hi>Fish</hi> the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> spake.</l>
               <l>Of great and strange <hi>effects</hi> b'inform'd you may,</l>
               <l>If you'll give <hi>credit</hi> to <hi>Apocrypha;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where th' <hi>Fishes</hi> gall they dry and pulverize</l>
               <l>To cure the whiteness of old <hi>Tobit</hi>'s eyes; (<hi>Tob.</hi> 6.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:10"/>
               <l>And of the <hi>Hearts</hi> perfume is made a <hi>spell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To charm the <hi>Devil</hi> sweetly into <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whether or not this <hi>Truth</hi> authentick be,</l>
               <l>We will not here dispute Authority.</l>
               <l>Only believe it with a Moral Faith,</l>
               <l>And now let's hear what <hi>Evangelium</hi> saith.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When the Collectors of the <hi>Tribute</hi> went</l>
               <l>To <hi>Christ</hi> for pay, to th' Seas <hi>he Simon</hi> sent,</l>
               <l>Who op'ning th' <hi>Fishes</hi> mouth, that he first took, Mat. 17.</l>
               <l>A piece of <hi>Money</hi> with a <hi>Silver Hook.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When at <hi>Emaus Christ</hi> alone appear'd <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</l>
               <l>To th'two Disciples that a <hi>Spirit</hi> fear'd,</l>
               <l>He asked them for meat, and the first <hi>Dish</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That he did eat of was a broiled <hi>Fish.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Christ</hi> another time appearance made,</l>
               <l>He found's <hi>Disciples</hi> at the <hi>Fishing Trade;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were toiling sore,</l>
               <l>Mending their Nets when <hi>Jesus</hi> stood on th'<hi>Shore.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Simon Peter</hi> saw it was the <hi>Lord, (Joh.</hi> 21.</l>
               <l>O'rjoy'd he was, and leaped over-board,</l>
               <l>Naked, girt only with his <hi>Fishers Coat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He cast himself down head-long from the <hi>Boat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This <hi>Peter</hi> durst not on the <hi>Waters</hi> pass,</l>
               <l>Without his <hi>Master,</hi> yet chief <hi>Fisher</hi> was;</l>
               <l>Chief <hi>Shepherd,</hi> &amp; first <hi>Pope,</hi> whose <hi>name (say some)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Descended to th'old <hi>Fisherman</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What if St. <hi>Peter</hi> ne'r to <hi>Rome</hi> was sent,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Scripture</hi> says he oft a <hi>Fishing</hi> went.</l>
               <l>What if he ne'r sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Bishop in <hi>Rome</hi>'s See,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Sea</hi> he was with th'<hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Zebedee. (Mar.</hi> 1.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:10"/>
               <l>Who long had toyl'd, and had nothing caught,</l>
               <l>Till Jesus bid them let down for a draught;</l>
               <l>In which a multitude though they did take,</l>
               <l>Its written there, their Nets it did not break;</l>
               <l>But strait <hi>retir'd themselves</hi> from thence and <hi>fed Mat.</hi> 4.</l>
               <l>Upon their <hi>broiled Fishes</hi> and their <hi>Bread.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's said they took an Hundred fifty three;</l>
               <l>Some of all kinds i'the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Galilee;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By which all sorts of Men is signifi'd,</l>
               <l>And the great <hi>Fishing</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> imply'd;</l>
               <l>How the <hi>Apostles</hi> by their <hi>Preaching</hi> shall,</l>
               <l>Both Poor and Rich, both Base and Noble call;</l>
               <l>And draw them with their Nets from the Worlds Sea</l>
               <l>To th'Ship of <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Felicity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Amos, Esay, Habakkuk</hi> compare <hi>Isa.</hi> 19.</l>
               <l>Things that of worth and great importance are,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Fishing, Drags,</hi> and <hi>Nets,</hi> and like to these, <hi>Can.</hi> 7.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are th'Wisemans Fishpools in the Canticles.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So doth <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Jeremy</hi> Jer. 16.</l>
               <l>Call <hi>Preachers Fishers</hi> in their <hi>Prophesie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose <hi>Doctrine</hi> is their <hi>Nets, which from these toys Ez.</hi> 47.10.</l>
               <l>Do draw Mens Souls into Eternal Joys.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Christ</hi> his power and God head did express Mat. 14.</l>
               <l>To th'<hi>hungry people</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He <hi>first made choice of Loaves, Lifes staff and then,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Two little Fishes fed Five thousand Men.</l>
               <l>Another time a multitude he fed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</l>
               <l>With few small Fishes and a little Bread.</l>
               <l>If we search Chronicles, we there may see</l>
               <l>The Art of <hi>Fishing</hi> from <hi>Antiquity:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:199384:11"/>
               <l>When Bishop <hi>Wilfrid</hi> turn'd to Christian Faith,</l>
               <l>The Heathen <hi>Saxons</hi> (an Historian saith)</l>
               <l>He teaches them this <hi>Art</hi> at first, and makes</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Those Nets catch fish, which did before catch snakes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He going with these <hi>Pagans</hi> to the Brook:</l>
               <l>Three hundred <hi>Fishes</hi> with their <hi>Nets</hi> he took,</l>
               <l>Strait he divides the spoil, and one part gets</l>
               <l>Himself; then <hi>furnished</hi> them that own'd the <hi>Nets:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The third part to the poor he did divide,</l>
               <l>Which made's Religion to be deifi'd,</l>
               <l>And gain'd him Converts, when he did bestow</l>
               <l>His Prayers above, with blessings here below.</l>
               <l>In fine if you look up to'th Azure sky</l>
               <l>And view the Circles in Astronomy,</l>
               <l>You there may see a Fish prefer'd so high</l>
               <l>The Heavens are with the Constellation grac'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pisces</hi> is next unto <hi>Aquarius</hi> plac'd;</l>
               <l>For least the Firmament a sign should lack,</l>
               <l>A Fish the Twelfth is in the Zodiack.</l>
               <l>Thus from the Ocean to the Stars, we can</l>
               <l>Advance the Praises of the Fisherman.</l>
               <l>And 'tis from Gospel and the Prophets seen,</l>
               <l>What honour, use of Fish, and Fishing's been.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ro. Nobbes.</hi> M. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:11"/>
            <head>THE Fishermans Wish.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WOuld I might live near <hi>Avon's</hi> flowry brink,</l>
               <l>And on the World, and my Creator think:</l>
               <l>Whilst others strive ill gotten goods t' embrace,</l>
               <l>Would I near <hi>Welland</hi> had a dwelling place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would I these harmless pastimes might pursue,</l>
               <l>And uncontroll'd might <hi>Ponds</hi> and <hi>Rivers</hi> view:</l>
               <l>Whilst others spend their time in base excess,</l>
               <l>In Drinking, Gaming, and in Wantonness.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would I might let my fancy feed its fill,</l>
               <l>And daily by fresh <hi>Rivers</hi> walk at will,</l>
               <l>Whilst others toyl in hunting, and perplext,</l>
               <l>Are with unquiet Recreations vext.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would I might view the Compass of the Sky,</l>
               <l>The flaming Chariot of the Worlds great eye,</l>
               <l>And fair <hi>Aurora</hi> lifting up her head,</l>
               <l>Blushing to rise from old <hi>Tithonus</hi> bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would I might walk in Woods and Forrests long,</l>
               <l>In whose cool Bowers the Birds sing many a Song;</l>
               <l>And in the Verdant Meadows fresh and green,</l>
               <l>Would I might fit and Court the Summers Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic Optat, R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:12"/>
            <head>THE Compleat Troller, OR, THE ART OF TROLLING.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Name and Nature of a <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A <hi>Pike</hi> is called in the Latin <hi>Lucius,</hi> either a <hi>Lucendo,</hi> from shining in the Waters, or else (which is more probable) from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Greek word for <hi>Lupus;</hi> for as the Wolf is the most ravenous and cruel among Beasts, so the <hi>Pike</hi> is most greedy and devouring among Fishes. So that <hi>Lupus Piscis</hi> tho it be proper for the <hi>Sea-Wolf,</hi> yet it is often used for the <hi>Pike</hi> it self, the fresh water <hi>Wolf.</hi> He is of so greedy and voracious a nature, that he doth not only prey upon small Fishes, <hi>Frogs,</hi> &amp;c. that come in his way in the Water, but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon Birds, and the Fowls of the Air:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199384:13"/> and (some say) he will fasten upon greater A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nimals. A <hi>German</hi> Writer reports for a certai<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> truth, That when he had his Mule to drink a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the River <hi>Rhine,</hi> she was caught so fast by he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> neather lipp with a <hi>Pike;</hi> that being sorely bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten and terrified at so unexpected an Assault<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> she suddenly threw up her head, and cast th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Fish upon the shore, which became a prey t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Master of the Mule. Out of this <hi>Pike</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> taken, when it was opened, two young Gees<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> or Goslins, a Fen-Duck, and the foot of<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Maid. If this Story be not creditable, because i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is so far fetch'd as from <hi>Germany,</hi> yet this i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> certain that a More-hen hath been found in th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> belly of a <hi>Pike</hi> taken out of our own Rivers<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and I have seen my self that a <hi>Pike</hi> hath rise<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and struck at a Swallow, that hath dip'd he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> wings upon the Waters; and have known the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that have used a live Sparrow for a Bait at Snap<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> An English Physician made this Observation i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his Travels in the Low Countries, That as they were passing the Rivers in little Boats, the <hi>Pike</hi> struck so swiftly and greedily at the small Fry for feed, that sometimes they shot themselve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> so far out of the Water, that they fell into th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Boat. This is another foreign Story, whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> we may parallel with one at home; how on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that had catch'd an Eel, and was pulling of the skin and washing it in a Mote, a <hi>Pike</hi> leap<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> at the <hi>Eel</hi> and fastened himself so to it, that h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199384:13"/> drew out both <hi>Eel</hi> and <hi>Pike.</hi> Of all the small Officers under this great Captain, a <hi>Perch</hi> is the most secure from his devouring jaws; on which <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e seldom adventures, except meer hunger <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ompels him: yet <hi>Albert</hi> says he will take a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>erch</hi> by the head, and kill it with his teeth first, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>est if he should gorge it a-live, the finns and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rickles might be offensive to his maw: nor <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oes he only tyrannize over all the small inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ants of his own dominions, and sometimes <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>respasses upon another Element, but often <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ransgresses the laws of Generation, and those <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>f his own species he unnaturally devours. This Common-wealth among the Fishes, is much <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ike Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s State of Nature, which is <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ut <hi>Status Belli,</hi> the Great Ones always devour <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he less; such is the Government, or rather <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>narchy in the Waters, where might will be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ure to overcome right, and the weakest go still <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o the Walls. A <hi>Pike</hi> is a Prince in his own Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uid Countrey, and like an Universal Monarch, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>an command all the Regiments of the Scaled <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rmy, can Lord it over all his Vassals, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ike a Potent Tyrant) can enslave all the Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ents in his own Territories without the least <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>esistance: Yet one profess'd enemy he hath, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat more powerful than himself, which is a <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>reature of an amphibious Nature, and can live <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y land as well as by water: This is a cunning <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd a choice Fisher, for he seldom takes any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199384:14"/> but the best and the biggest Fish: He is much esteem'd of in some Countries, especially in <hi>Sweden,</hi> where he is kept tame for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, and taught so much craft and dexterity, that the Cook will send him out of the Kitchin when he wants a Dish of Fish, and he will go strait to the Pond and fetch them. 'Tis a strange tale if true, and we had better believe it, than go so far to disprove it: I never looked upon an <hi>Otter</hi> to be such a docible and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable a Creature; tho perhaps those of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countrey may differ much in their Nature from ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Parts and Lineaments of a <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS to the shape and proportion of this great devourer, the figure of his Body is very long, his back broad, and almost square; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together equal to the lowest Finns: his head is lean and very bony, which bones in his head some have resembled to things of mysterious consequence: One of which they commonly compare to the Cross, another to the Spear<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> three other to those bloody Nails which wer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Instruments of our Saviours passion: If thos<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> comparisons smell any thing of superstition,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199384:14"/> yet as to Physical use, those bones may be profitable. For the jaw-bone beaten to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, may be helpful for <hi>Pleurisies</hi> and the sharpness of <hi>Urine;</hi> some do approve of it as a Remedy for the pain in the Heart and Stomach; others affirm that the small bones pulverized, may be fitly used to dry up Sores, and many the like Medicinal qualities are attributed to the <hi>Pikes</hi> head. An Ancient Author writing of his Nature of things, does discover a Stone in the Brain of a Pike much like unto a Chrystal: <hi>Gesner</hi> himself the great <hi>Naturalist,</hi> testifies that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e found in the head of a little <hi>Pike</hi> two white Stones. As to the shape of his Head, his Snowt <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s long, which some have compared to the Bill <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r Beak of a Goose. His lower Jaw is far longer than his upper; and in it are placed many Teeth, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ot orderly disposed, but of divers ranks and orders. His Eyes are of a golden colour, and very quick sighted, as are all sorts of Fish. Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Belly is always white, but his Back and Sides <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re of a black and speckled yellow. His Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ricle is very large and capacious, and his Throat <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hort, as we may see by his prey which he hath <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ewly taken and not digested; part of it will come up into his mouth, but this is when he <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eizes upon a great prize. A Credible Author <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ffirms that he saw a <hi>Pike</hi> of that wonderful <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>igness, that had another within him conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ably great, and that within had a <hi>Water-Rat</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199384:15"/> in its Belly; So that the Ventricle of the great one must needs be exceeding large and extensive <hi>Gesner</hi> likewise observes that his Heart and Galls is very Medicinable to cure <hi>Agues,</hi> abate <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors,</hi> &amp;c. and that his biting is venemous and hard to be cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Age and growth of a <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS to the encrease and vivacity of this devouring Fish, some Historians have asserted that he will live to an incredible Age▪ and that he will carry half as many Years a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Scales upon his Back. Our Fore-quoted Autho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Gesner,</hi> relates in his Natural History that a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Pike</hi> was taken out of a Pond of the Emperou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Frederick,</hi> that had lived 260 and odd Years▪ which appears by the date in a Brass Ring whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> lay hidden and grown over in his Gills, and had this Inscription written in Latin, <hi>Ego su<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> illi piscis huic Stagno omnium primus impofit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> per Mundi Rectoris Frederici secundi manus di<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> quinto</hi> Octobris, 1497. But whether our Fait<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> will give us leave to believe this or not, it is no<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> material to our Disquisitions; for though w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cannot prove him to be so longevous as to reac<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Hundreds, it is certain he will live to some score<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199384:15"/> of Years; and one of 40 or 45 inches, which are of the largest size, may possibly consist of as many Years as Inches; and some of our own Countreymen have known and observ'd a <hi>Pike</hi> to come within Ten Years of the distinct age of Man, and had liv'd longer had not fate hasten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Death by a violent hand. One of 40 inches (I said) might haply be of so many years standing; not that a <hi>Pike</hi> grow just about an Inch in a year, for that is a thing that is hard to determine, some grow faster, some slower, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diversity of their Water and their Feed: River Fish are thought to grow much fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than Pond Fish; except the Pond be very large and have a good stream run through it: for there is nothing helps so much to the feeding of a <hi>Pike</hi> as fresh Water. That's the reason why a <hi>Pike</hi> will not bite well after a great Rain. <hi>Jacks</hi> or <hi>Pickerills</hi> grow faster than great ones, and I have observed in a cleer and springing Brook, that a <hi>Jack</hi> spawn'd in <hi>March</hi> will take a Bait in <hi>October</hi> following, and will be encreased to Eighteen Inches the next <hi>March.</hi> In standing Water, as Motes and Ponds, he grows nothing so fast; for to try the experiment, I have taken one out with a Cast-net in <hi>May,</hi> Measured him and Mark'd him on his Tail, and about <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> I have taken the same fish, as appear'd by the Mark, and then measured him again and he hath not encreased in length above two Inches, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199384:16"/> very little in Breadth. A River Fish will grow very fast till he come to be 24 or near 30 Inches, then he stands a little more at astay, and spreads himself in thickness; after that he will grow a long time, and be much longer growing to his full bigness from 30 Inches, than he was encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to that proportion. He is a great Breeder and Multiplier, as we may see in those places that are preserv'd, how soon a River is full stock'd. Small <hi>Jacks</hi> shew themselves much after a Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flood, every Ditch is then full of <hi>Pickerills,</hi> and the Fenns are so abundantly stor'd with them, that you may buy an Horse load for a shilling. Its the Spring Tide that brings them up most, for about <hi>Midsummer</hi> and after they much decrease <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd diminish in their number; some being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with Snares and Bow-nets, some with Trol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and many little ones devoured by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: So that in the Stocking of a Pond, the wisest course is to put in all your <hi>Jacks</hi> as near as you can of a bigness, for a <hi>Pike</hi> of 30 Inches will make no bones of one of 16. As to the encrease of them, some are apt to grow more in length, others more in Breath and Thickness; which latter sort are the best fed and the firmest Fishes; for a lean, slender <hi>Pike,</hi> though he may seem to advance and improve in length, yet he is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Waster; for if he hath received any outward hurt, or wound, either by the <hi>Otter</hi> or by a strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his own species, or is inwardly pricked by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199384:16"/> the Hook or any casualty, yet still he will live and eat his Meat, and be as hungry as <hi>Pharao</hi>'s lean Kine, which devoured the fat ones: he will be yet for Plunder and greedy as ever, tho he neither thrive nor grow; this I observed in a large <hi>Pike</hi> which I took in a wasting conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he had a long Hook in his Belly, and the end of the Wire hung out of his Mouth; he might probably have been long in that declining estate, and so might have continued a considerable time, though he fall away, and must at last ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily die of a Consumption. There are several circumstances of time and place which may be very advantageous and conduce much to the growth of a <hi>Pike,</hi> a still shady unfrequented place, where he is not affrighted and disturbed at his Feed is very Commodious for his rest and repast; especially if his Shelter be thick and convenient for him: for if a Ditch joyn upon the River, or a Spring or small Brook run into it, his abode will be more pleasing and delightsome; if it be a solitary and retired corner, not beaten with Fishers and the often visits of his flatering Friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Seat and Harbour of a <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Place and Harbour of a <hi>Pike</hi> is usually amongst or near a Bank of Weeds; for he does not always confine himself to his bed and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199384:17"/> lye close like a <hi>Fox</hi> in his den, but often shoots out and sports in the cleer stream; and (like the great <hi>Leviathan</hi>) takes his pastime in the middle of the Waters. The Weeds indeed are his chiefest refuge and his Sanctuary, if he be affrighted by a Net or the sudden disturbance of his approaching Enemy; he then strikes into his accustomed Harbour, and there keeps his Garison. Those weeds where he most delights to make his Residence, are Flags and Bulrushes; if there be none of those, then <hi>Candocks</hi> have the next honour to entertain this princely Guest. There are other Weeds where he thinks fit to make his abode, as Reeds, green Fog, and a Weed with a small leaf, which he often frequents, especially about <hi>October,</hi> when they begin to rot. If a place be very thick and weedy, you cannot so easily guess where his Lodgings are, but if the River be free from weeds, only here and there a bank or bed of Bullrushes, you may safely conclude those are his retirements and his baiting places: If your River be very broad, deep, and streight like a Scoure, it will be so much the more difficult to find his recess; and if there be but few fish, it will be next to seeking a Needle in a Bottle of Hay; for in such a kind of false River you may Troll perhaps from Morning till Night and scarce get a bite. But if such a place be little beaten, and have plenty of <hi>Fish</hi> you may have sport enough to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199384:17"/> encourage you to the same place; but then you must arm your self with a great deal of patience, and fish it very true and slow. There's not so much variety and delight in <hi>Trolling</hi> such a River, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is all along even and alike, and you cannot conceive where your prey lies; this you may call Hap-hazard, and expect a bite every throw, though you go three or four hours, and neither see nor feel any Fish but your own Bait. Some there are that place their sport in Hopes, and take as much delight in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation as others doe in frution; but a little En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement does well; not only for the profits sake (as something has some savour) but also to save the credit and keep away despair from the Melancholy <hi>Fisherman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The best and securest way of Fishing these wide Reaches, is by drawing the bait along the sides next to you, except you can search the breadth of it, and throw over to the farther side; but that is but dull and slow Sport, and it will spend a great deal of time to <hi>Troll</hi> the length of a Furlong. If your River consists of pits, which is the quickest and most delightsome way of <hi>Trolling,</hi> you must have a special regard to the top and bottom of the Pit. A <hi>Pike</hi> may be taken sometimes in the middle, but his chiefest Seat and Habitation is at the bottom of the Pit; and this I have often observed, that where one <hi>Pike</hi> hath been taken at the Mouth, another
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199384:18"/> hath been found at the feet or bottom of the Pit.</p>
               <p>These are the ordinary places; yet according to the variety of Weather and Seasons of the Year, a <hi>Pike</hi> will alter and change his dwelling. In the Winter he usually couches very nigh the ground, and gets into the deepest and obscurest places; about the latter end of <hi>February,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> he begins to be weary of his melancholly repose, and to raise himself a little from the bottom, and is more active in seeking his feed: At the latter end of <hi>March,</hi> or sometimes the middle, he shoots into the scoures, and there leaves the Spawn to multiply accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its kind. In <hi>April</hi> and <hi>May</hi> he still gets higher, and advances himself into the shallows; and if he may lie unmolested there, he will so continue most part of Summer; in <hi>September</hi> he begins to retreat again, and removes himself from his accustomed harbour to visit his Winter Quarters, which will be much the same as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if no floods disorder him: This is his yearly course to change according to heat or cold, so that a <hi>Pike,</hi> like a Person of Quality, hath both a Winter and a Summer House. As to his dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Transactions, he thus disposes of himself: In a hot gleamy day, he gets to the Surface of the Water, as if he had a desire to exchange his Element, to enjoy the comfortable influence of the Airy Region, he then scorns to be tempted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199384:18"/> with a Bait, and can live all day with a little more nourishment than the Motes in the Sun: for you can no sooner offer him the kindness of a deceitful Bit, but he's gone as swift as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to abscond himself in his lowest retirements. There are some that will make such brags of their Art, that they have the confidence to say, They can find a <hi>Pike</hi> as easily in his seat, as an old <hi>Hare-finder</hi> can take Puss in her Furm; and that the same <hi>Pike</hi> will as infallibly take your Bait, as an hungry Dog will leap at a Crust: They would make you believe they are good <hi>Accomptants,</hi> and such <hi>Water Arithmeticians,</hi> that they can tell the number of the <hi>Fish</hi> in the River as well as <hi>Graziers</hi> can count their Sheep and Beasts in their Pastures. These Stories are too Romantick to gain the credit of sober <hi>Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> though one that hath had much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and made it his business, may give a near guess where the <hi>Fish</hi> lies: some places are more probable than others, though you will often meet with them in the middle as well as by the sides, and sometimes unexpectedly where there is no conveniency of shelter or repast. A Ford that is cleer and gravelly at the bottom, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it have a Spit adjoyning to it that is indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent deep and weedy, is looked upon as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable place: for though they generally affect a deep Water, yet they will get as near as they can to a Ford or Shallow; where they delight
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199384:19"/> themselves, and sport with the little fry, so a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Scoures and Pits that are near Mills, eithe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> above or below them, commonly well stor'<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with Fish: A Mill Dam that is deep and weedy<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is an approved Receptacle for them. Tho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Rivers that are streight and level, are not<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> good to Fish, as those that are crooked and hav<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> many corners and turnings: for the Fish wi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> get into those Creeks and Channels, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hide themselves in their private apartments.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the water be narrow, it is more pleasing for t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Troller;</hi> for where it is very broad and deep<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> there is more uncertainty in their <hi>Seat</hi> and <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour,</hi> if it be narrow, you may <hi>Fish</hi> both side<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and sooner chop upon them, you will then g<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> on the the faster; and with more courage a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> alacrity drive forward to your journeys en<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> But this is chiefly as every one fancies, for so<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> desire the widest places they can find, and the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to fix themselves two or three hours without at<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> considerable motion: I never approv'd of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> dull way, as thinking it needless and impertine<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to cast three or four times in one and the sa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Place, because a <hi>Pike</hi> if he bites at all, common<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> rises at it the first throw, tho he may sometim<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> snap at it, when you have the least thoughts<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him. As to the Nature or Constitution of the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver, the deeper is generally the better and the saf<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Harbour; altho he delights much in a mid<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Retirement, about four foot in depth is a rig<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199384:19"/> proportion, and the best pitch for the <hi>Troller;</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>or if it be much deeper, they are the more difficult to stir, and harder to find; and if <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hallower, they will be apt to see you, and so <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hun the inticements of a Treacherous Friend. Small <hi>Jacks</hi> will often lye within two or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ometimes one foot in Water; its the wisest course in such places to keep at a distance and not come nigh the River till the Bait is in.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the best Seasons for Trolling.</head>
               <p>THere are some that pretend to <hi>Trolling,</hi> and yet Observe no Time or Season to be better than another: A <hi>Pike</hi> indeed will bite more or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ess at any time, and the <hi>Fisherman</hi> may happen <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pon some sport, let him set out when he will; but <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o go out so at all adventures, is a very uncrtain <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd unsecure way: for as to the <hi>Heat</hi> in <hi>Summer</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Frost</hi> and <hi>Snow</hi> in <hi>Winter,</hi> he had better make <hi>Hay</hi> in the one, and sit by the <hi>Fire</hi> in <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he other. Some will brag so much of their <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ardy Constitutions, that they can break the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ce</hi> with one hand, and take out <hi>Fish</hi> with the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ther, and can slide a <hi>Trolling</hi> (like <hi>Dutchmen</hi>) <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n their <hi>Scates,</hi> and not be sensible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lemeny of the <hi>Air:</hi> they will be still for <hi>Fishing,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199384:20"/> when the Weather is more proper for <hi>Fowling;</hi> they will pretend they can charm the <hi>Fish</hi> at <hi>Christmas</hi> with a sweetned Bait, and to be more admired, will present their Landlord with a <hi>Pike</hi> at <hi>New-Years-tide;</hi> These (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess) are <hi>Artists</hi> far beyond our Profession, i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> their performances be as large as their promises.</p>
               <p>There are some <hi>Days</hi> (we grant) in the depth of <hi>Winter,</hi> as in <hi>December</hi> or <hi>January,</hi> that a <hi>Man</hi> may pick out to stand two or three hours, by the River-side, but the Weather must be Open and Temperate, and about the middle of the day: such a <hi>Winter</hi> as the last was in 81 might be very favourable to the sport, and there was few days but what might have been serviceable for the <hi>Trollers</hi> Diversion; the great <hi>Fish</hi> will be then soonest enticed with the Bait at that time of the Year, because they lye dee<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and are not so careful of their own preservation▪ There is another great advantage for the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Troller,</hi> that the Weeds are then down, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> rotten, which before were a great hinderanc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> both from throwing the Bait, as also in keepin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Fish</hi> from the sight of it; for though a <hi>Pi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> delights much among the Weeds, and doe<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> usually make his abode there, yet it is very diff<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cult to take him there, except it be with th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Snap; for if you give him the liberty of run<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning and playing with your Bait, he winds him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self so fast about the Weeds, that you may b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199384:20"/> in some danger of losing both your <hi>Fish</hi> and your <hi>Hook,</hi> if your Line be not very Strong: If you take a Snap too, you will be troubled with them, for they are great Enemies to that. To begin the Year then and the <hi>Fishermans</hi> Recreations, <hi>February</hi> is the first and none of the worst <hi>Months</hi> he can pitch upon for his sport, after <hi>Candlemas</hi> if the season be moderate and the water in tune (which is very rare then) for if it be not a flood, as it is often at that time, yet the Ditches and Brooks are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly so rank and full, that it is but indifferent <hi>Fishing;</hi> but if it chance to be a dry season and open, it is one of the best <hi>Months.</hi> So is <hi>March</hi> very seasonable and auspicious to the <hi>Troller,</hi> excepting the time of <hi>Spawning,</hi> which usually begins about the middle, unless the Spring be very forward; and then they will be sick sooner. The Snap is then the only way to deceive them, for if you fish at Pouch you may have many <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ites, but scarse take one, except it be a <hi>Male-fish.</hi> These two <hi>Months</hi> will try the <hi>Fishermans</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>atience, whether he be <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Weather</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>roof; the next is <hi>April,</hi> which will make him <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mends for his former sufferings; and is a <hi>Month</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o inviting to sport, that it is both pleasant and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rofitable; the chirping <hi>Birds</hi> do then begin to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eek their <hi>Males,</hi> and the long silent <hi>Cuckee</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat forsook her colder <hi>Climate,</hi> does again <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>alute her sprouting branches, and tell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199384:21"/> us the News of an approaching <hi>Summer:</hi> Yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> may then please your self to see the tende<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Swallow</hi> so ioyful at her first flight, when sh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> seems to make obeisance to your Bait, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> displays her Wings upon the surface of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Waters. This <hi>Month</hi> you will find most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to your pastime, because the Weed<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> which have couch'd all <hi>Winter,</hi> have not ye<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> erected their Heads to annoy the Bait, o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> frustrate the hopes of an impatient <hi>Fisherma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> This <hi>Month</hi> (I say) is usually successful fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> these diversions, both because the River is the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cleer of Fog and Filth; and also that the <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> which have lately cast their <hi>Spawn,</hi> are now mo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hungry and ready for their prey; there is no<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> little fear of their forsaking your Bait as the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> did in <hi>March.</hi> They are not yet arrived to tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> fatness, and firmness, which they will ge<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Summer,</hi> but are many of them flamp an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thin; the <hi>individium</hi> decreasing to multiply th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> species. The beginning of <hi>May</hi> is likewise ve<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> seasonable, especially if it hits with the <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verb</hi> to be Cold and Windy; towards the latte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> end of it the <hi>Weeds</hi> spring up, and are ver<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> offensive to the <hi>Hook;</hi> then begins the <hi>Trolle<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Vacation, which continues till the latter end<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>August</hi> or the beginning of <hi>September;</hi> yet tho<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that are afraid of an <hi>Ague</hi> at <hi>Spring,</hi> or <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may choose themselves the coolest cloudy <hi>d<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> they can find in <hi>June</hi> or <hi>July</hi> to exercise the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199384:21"/> Skill; but then they will be sure to take more <hi>Weeds</hi> than <hi>Fish.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Fall of <hi>Autumnal</hi> season, <hi>October</hi> is the principal <hi>Month,</hi> the <hi>Wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her</hi> being then temperate, and the <hi>Weeds</hi> which were st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g and high before, do now die and fall to the bottom. The <hi>Rivers</hi> are then generally low, which is a great advantage one way, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cause the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh</hi> are more easily found in their Harbours, when they leave the <hi>Shallows</hi> and <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>res,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the <hi>Pits</hi> and deepest places: A <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is now very firm and fat, having had the benefit of the <hi>Summers</hi> feed; and if the <hi>Weather</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue dry and not extraordinary cold, you may take in part of <hi>November,</hi> which will add much <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o your sport, because the <hi>Weeds</hi> will be the more wasted and rotten; but if a flood comes in <hi>October,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> you may lay aside your <hi>Tackling</hi> for that <hi>Season:</hi> for great <hi>Rivers</hi> (like great <hi>Vessels</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long in filling, and slowly mounting to their full height, are again long in falling and settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing; so that the <hi>Water</hi> will be thick and out of order, except frost or much fair Weather comes to clear it. In small <hi>Brooks</hi> and <hi>Rivolets</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t is not so, but you may <hi>Fish</hi> there again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Week or less after the <hi>Flood.</hi> If such incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies put off your designed <hi>Sport,</hi> you must be content to desist till the fol ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng <hi>Spring,</hi> when the days will be longer, though haply the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199384:22"/> Weather colder. Now as to the time of the day, the <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening</hi> is most delightsome in <hi>Summer;</hi> because towards <hi>Noon</hi> the <hi>Fish</hi> get up to the top of the <hi>Water,</hi> and are more mindful of their play than their meat. If the day be clear and calm, a <hi>Snare</hi> is more proper than a <hi>Bait;</hi> for the least motion you can make with your <hi>Line</hi> will affright a <hi>Fish</hi> that lies high; and if he be once mov'd and put to the flight, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the art you can use will not entice him to your <hi>Bait</hi> again: besides that, it will then be too hot for sport; for heat creates no appetite in any thing, much less in <hi>Fish:</hi> its the Wind, and the cooler Clouds, when <hi>Zephirus</hi> curles the <hi>Waves</hi> with a brisk and delightsome <hi>Gale,</hi> that invites a <hi>Fish</hi> to repast; these hot and sultrey da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are fittest for the <hi>stote,</hi> when the <hi>Fish</hi> are for some light and slender diet; and the <hi>Angler</hi> hath the best pastime with his <hi>Flies</hi> and <hi>Bees,</hi> &amp;c. At such a time of year early or late is the best <hi>Fishing,</hi> if it be in the <hi>Night.</hi> But as to the <hi>Winter</hi> or <hi>Spring Quarter,</hi> one part of the day is as favourable as the other; for then the Sun being not so hot, it neither molests the <hi>Fisher,</hi> nor takes away the <hi>Fishes</hi> stomacks; if the day be dark and cloudy, you will find but little difference; if any, the <hi>Noon-tide</hi> is the best, or about Ten or Eleven of the Clock; you will be then glad of a warm blast, when your fingers can scarce feel whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>Fish</hi> or <hi>Flesh.</hi> Some are very scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199384:22"/> concerning the <hi>Wind,</hi> and will not stir cut a <hi>foot</hi> except it stand in what <hi>corner</hi> they would have it; though upon such a Nicety I scarse ever denied my self a <hi>day</hi> of diversion. A <hi>Northern Wind</hi> indeed is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re sharp and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and will weary the <hi>Fishermans</hi> patience, because <hi>Boreas</hi> his <hi>Breath</hi> is more nipping than that of his fellows, and the <hi>North East</hi> carries a <hi>Proverb</hi> with it, enough to discourage a <hi>fresh Water Souldier;</hi> yet this I have observed, that in a right and seasonable time of <hi>year,</hi> the <hi>Fish</hi> will <hi>bite</hi> let the <hi>Wind</hi>-stand where it will. The <hi>South</hi> and the <hi>South-west</hi> have the general applause, because they are more pleasing and delightsome to the <hi>Troller;</hi> and tis granted that the <hi>Fish</hi> may then rise more briskly and quicker at the <hi>Bait,</hi> and perhaps they may then have more sport, than when the <hi>Wind</hi> is contrary; yet this is as certain, that the colder the <hi>Wind</hi> is, the closer the <hi>Fish</hi> lye to the bottom, and the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their harbour; which may hinder you of having so many <hi>bites,</hi> as when they lye out and more open in a warmer <hi>day:</hi> yet the <hi>Air</hi> being cold and sharp, it makes them hungry; and if you be careful you may have as many <hi>Fish</hi> as <hi>bites:</hi> besides a <hi>Fish</hi> of any bigness, is too cunning to be cheated of his life, if he lyes not securely in the <hi>deeps,</hi> or invisible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>weeds;</hi> for as old <hi>Birds</hi> are too subtile to be taken with chaffe, so an old <hi>Fish</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199384:23"/> that hath been already prick'd in the <hi>Gills</hi> or the <hi>Guts,</hi> is very cautious in making a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cond adventure. All the principal and chiefest time for <hi>Trolling</hi> may be epitomiz'd into four <hi>Months,</hi> two of which attend the <hi>Spring</hi> and two the <hi>Fall;</hi> part of <hi>March</hi> may conveniently be left out, which will only tantalize with <hi>Bites</hi> and afford you no <hi>Fish,</hi> if you use the <hi>Pouch;</hi> neither will they then <hi>bite</hi> so freely as they will about a <hi>Fortnight</hi> after, they are then very averse and indifferent in their <hi>feeding;</hi> the reason of which some do ascribe to the multitude of <hi>Frogs</hi> which do then engender and breed in the <hi>Waters;</hi> though I have not been altogether of that opinion: for supposing the <hi>Fish</hi> do feed upon <hi>Frogs</hi> then, which I could seldom observe, especially in the deep <hi>Streams</hi> and running <hi>Waters,</hi> where the <hi>Frogs</hi> very rarely come; for they generate for the most part in <hi>Pits</hi> and standing <hi>Pools</hi> amongst <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>mire:</hi> yet notwithstanding this that the <hi>Fish</hi> do prey upon them at that time, yet it will not hinder your sport so much, but that they will oft take your <hi>Bait;</hi> for a <hi>Pike</hi> is of that greedy and rapacious Nature, that although he hath lately made a good meal of <hi>Frogs,</hi> yet he will not deny to taste of a <hi>Roach</hi> for his second course: He takes so much pleasure and delight in eating, that he never cares to stint himself; or <hi>Physically,</hi> for his <hi>healths</hi> sake, to be content
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199384:23"/> with a moderate diet: for I have often taken him so soon after his feeding, that he hath had part of his meat in his mouth; having newly swallowed so large a <hi>Fish,</hi> that his <hi>Ventricle</hi> was neither capable to receive or digest it quickly: sometimes I have taken him with two or three <hi>Baits</hi> in his <hi>Maw;</hi> sometimes with a great <hi>Roch</hi> or <hi>Daze;</hi> sometimes with one of his own species, very seldom with a <hi>Frog</hi> in his belly; a <hi>Frog</hi> is accounted a good <hi>Bait</hi> once by the year, that is about <hi>Hay-time,</hi> when it looks bright and yellow, though then it is something difficult to find; in <hi>March</hi> they are very plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but are not of that golden colour, to make the <hi>Fish</hi> so much enamoured with their beauty. This may be granted then, that a <hi>Pike</hi> will feed to that excess and fulness, that he cannot gorge your <hi>Bait,</hi> yet will he rise and shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and make many offers, having such a good will to it, that you may often catch him with the <hi>Snap.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Feed of a <hi>Pike,</hi> and when he is fattest.</head>
               <p>IF you divide the Year into four Quarters, a <hi>Pike</hi> is good three of them; the <hi>Spring</hi> only being excepted. I could never find any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199384:24"/> difference in the eating of it. It is an usual saying, That a <hi>Pike</hi> and a <hi>Buck</hi> are in sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son together; that is in <hi>July</hi> and <hi>August:</hi> He is then very firm, and his parts hard and solid; you will find little alteration in <hi>September</hi> and <hi>October,</hi> which are the chiefest Months for the goodness of a <hi>Fish,</hi> he having enjoyed the quiet and unmolested feed of the fore-going Summer; in this we suppose a <hi>Pike</hi> of a considerable growth and bigness; for a small <hi>Jack</hi> eats al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways loose and washy; for he (like many <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restrial Animals</hi>) grows too fast to be fat, and therefore would be let alone till he encreases to greater dimensions. One about Two Foot or Twenty six Inches, is most grateful to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> and a <hi>Male Fish</hi> of that size is generally fat and delicious. <hi>Physicians</hi> affirm that the <hi>Chyle</hi> or <hi>Juice</hi> of such a <hi>Fish</hi> concocted, is more wholesome to the <hi>Stomach,</hi> than one of the larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>proportion;</hi> though all <hi>Fish</hi> are naturally light and of easy digestion. A <hi>Pike</hi> indeed cannot be too bigg to make a present, or to spend on a publick occasion, to give noble and sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Entertainment. It will then be very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and acceptable, when the <hi>Pike</hi> is answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the company, and the sawce answerable to the <hi>Pike;</hi> for if it swims not in sawce and liquor, it had been better still swimming in the <hi>River.</hi> Such a <hi>Fish</hi> (which may be supposed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 40 inches) will feed to an incredible fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199384:24"/> some say far more, but I can testifie that a quart of fat hath been taken out of the belly of such a one: it must necessarily be a great charge and expence to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a <hi>Pike</hi> to that bigness, insomuch that some have credibly affirmed, that a Pike i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as costly and as long a feeding as an <hi>Ox<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Now a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the difference of <hi>Fish,</hi> one out of a River that is sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, is far better and sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than one fed in a <hi>Pond;</hi> except he be taken out of the <hi>Pond,</hi> and put into a running <hi>Stream,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> clear a while before he be eaten. Some that are curious, have <hi>Stews</hi> and <hi>Fountains</hi> for that purpose, and can draw them at their pleasure, chusing the sattest, and throwing in the rest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. As to the <hi>Feed</hi> of a <hi>Pike,</hi> the small <hi>Fry</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l keep him very well, though not so much to make him thrive and fatten; <hi>Griggs</hi> or small <hi>Eels</hi> cut on the backs, and cast in a few at a time, are his most nourishing and fattening di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. The way of throwing <hi>Bullocks Blood</hi> into a <hi>Pond, Panches</hi> and <hi>Guts,</hi> cannot be so cleanly and wholesome <hi>Feed;</hi> much less is their practice approvable, that allow their <hi>Fish</hi> no better fare then <hi>Carrion,</hi> young <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lps</hi> or <hi>Kitlins,</hi> or such kind of loathsome meat: it is possible that <hi>Fish</hi> may feed upon such stinking and noysome <hi>food,</hi> and gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w fat withal, but they are only fit for them to eat, that feed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m with such trash; for it is not imaginable how those <hi>Fish</hi> should be sweet and wholesome, that live upon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199384:25"/> such foul and unclean meat: however, if they can perswade themselves that those <hi>Fish</hi> so fouly fed, are equally pleasant and toothsome with those that fare better; yet the very conceit and fancy that works upon some queasie <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs,</hi> may represent that nauceous and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, which is really sweet and nourishing. A<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to the difference of <hi>Fish,</hi> you may easily distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish a <hi>Fed Pike</hi> from one in a wasting condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for they differ in the <hi>col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur,</hi> which is usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally yellow and spotted in a fat, but white and pale in a thin lean <hi>Fish:</hi> you may also distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish them by the weight and bulk, if they be much of a length; observing likewise the breadth of the back and the sides: for those <hi>Fish</hi> that have full and extended bellies, are often deceitful, and may be full of <hi>Spawns</hi> instead of fat: The <hi>Male-Pike</hi> is generally firm and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting to the Eater; but the <hi>Spawners</hi> or <hi>Sow-Fish</hi> (as s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me call them) are out of season great part of <hi>Summer:</hi> for both before and after they have cast their <hi>Spawn,</hi> they are scarce worth the <hi>Trollers</hi> labour: Some do observe that they mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply twice by the year, at the beginning o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Spring, and again the latter end of Summer▪ which is not at all improbable. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny circumstances that conduce much to the feeding of a <hi>Pike,</hi> as first a convenient <hi>Harbour;</hi> for they that lie among <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>foggy places</hi> do prove the fattest; they are there secure from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199384:25"/> the assaults and disturbance of Enemies, and enjoy a more safe and contented repose: Rest and quietness being as natural and helpful to their <hi>feeding</hi> as to other Creatures: Again there is some Water may be more <hi>feeding</hi> and <hi>nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> than other: A thicker sort of <hi>Water,</hi> if it be not soul and muddy, is of a better consistency, and the parts better disposed and qualified for <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi> than those of a more thin and rarified substance; for it is a <hi>Rule</hi> in <hi>Philosophy,</hi> that no <hi>Element</hi> that is pure and without mixture, is <hi>consentanteous</hi> for <hi>nourishing;</hi> so that they have put it among their Vulgar Errors, that the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelion</hi> cannot live by <hi>Air</hi> alone, or the <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> by <hi>Fire:</hi> so may we deny that <hi>Fish</hi> can live by pure <hi>Water,</hi> or by <hi>Respiration,</hi> or sucking in those slender <hi>Particles</hi> of his beloved <hi>Element,</hi> without the concurrence and assistance of some grosser and terrene qualities, which are inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled with these <hi>Liquid Bodies.</hi> This is the reason why <hi>Fish</hi> are the fattest, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together the sweetest, among <hi>Weeds</hi> and thick <hi>Fog;</hi> when they live and thrive with a little more refreshment, than what they receive from that fatness which the soyl imparts: if there be great store of <hi>Rubbish</hi> in a <hi>Pond</hi> or <hi>River,</hi> there needs a less supply of adventitious <hi>feed:</hi> it is a common observation, that after a glut of <hi>Rain,</hi> or some great <hi>Showres,</hi> a <hi>Pike</hi> never <hi>bites</hi> well, because he hath lately fed upon those fresh
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199384:26"/>
                  <hi>Streams</hi> that come in from the <hi>Banks</hi> and the <hi>Ditches;</hi> and indeed that reason may be proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true; for though the <hi>Rain water</hi> of it self can have but little or no more strengthening than that already in the <hi>River;</hi> yet it scouring through the <hi>Channels,</hi> and washing the <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> as it passeth, may from thence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a firmer and more solid substance; which may make it more glutinous and congruous for <hi>nutrition.</hi> It is possible that a <hi>Pike</hi> may live a great while in a cleer <hi>Pool,</hi> where there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther small <hi>Fry</hi> to prey upon, nor <hi>Harbour</hi> to shelter in, nor any quantity of <hi>Fog</hi> which might give him subsistance; yet certainly he will be much dissatisfied with that course of life, being as much discontented with those short com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as one that hath not been used to a Prison-life, is there put in and fed with nothing but <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Water.</hi> I could never hear of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that made tryal of this, meerly for experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment sake; but this is confess'd, that some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons have put a great stock of <hi>Pikes</hi> into their <hi>Ponds,</hi> and have not regarded to put in meat proportionable to their number, yet have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served it many years, denying both themselves and others the liberty of <hi>Fishing</hi> in it; have drawn it afterwards, expecting a plentiful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and have found nothing answerable to their expectations: so great a diminutio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of them must either be caused by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199384:26"/>
                  <hi>Otter,</hi> or secretly by stealth or the like (which is scarce probable, they being kept so diligently, and watched so narrowly) or else they must infallibly languish and die for want of their accustomed <hi>feed.</hi> Some <hi>Fish</hi> might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape in such a mortality of them, and might still live and grow, but it is to be conceived, that they are those that were bred and wonted to the place, and not those that were taken out of the <hi>River</hi> and put into the <hi>Pond</hi> to <hi>feed:</hi> for alteration of <hi>Water</hi> among <hi>Fish,</hi> as well as change of <hi>Air</hi> or <hi>Ground</hi> among <hi>Beasts,</hi> is of much consequence, being very beneficial to some, and destructive to others.</p>
               <p>Not but that they are much advanced that are translated from a worse to a better conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: It is well known that <hi>Fen-Fish</hi> brought up into clear and higher <hi>Waters,</hi> will thrive much and be sweeter; but whether those that are bred in <hi>Brooks</hi> and small <hi>Streams,</hi> carried and put into <hi>Fen-Ditches</hi> will change for the better or the worse, is worth our enquiring.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Baits for <hi>Trolling.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving already discours'd of the <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>Pike,</hi> and discovered his <hi>Harbour</hi> and <hi>Feed,</hi> and the time and seasons most proper
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199384:27"/> to take him; the next work will be to provide <hi>Instruments</hi> and <hi>Tackling,</hi> as likewise <hi>Baits</hi> fit and suitable to every <hi>Season.</hi> Some there are that vary their <hi>Baits</hi> according to the time of the year, using small <hi>Fish</hi> in <hi>Winter,</hi> and <hi>Frogs,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Summer.</hi> I cannot disapprove of that way, though I seldom made use of others then a small <hi>Fish,</hi> a <hi>Roch,</hi> or a <hi>Dace,</hi> sometimes a <hi>Gudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which if it be large, is an excellent <hi>Bait,</hi> it being a sweet <hi>Fish,</hi> a <hi>Pike</hi> very rarely leave<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> it; it is of a dark colour and complexion, and therefore is most proper to be used in a brigh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> day, or when the <hi>Waters</hi> are very clear and transparent: If the <hi>River</hi> be any thing muddy▪ or the <hi>Weather</hi> cloudy, then a <hi>Roch</hi> or a littl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Dace,</hi> or a <hi>Bleak</hi> newly taken, are the be<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Baits</hi> can be made use of; the fresher they ar<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the better, for if they lie dead but one night▪ especially in hot Weather, they may fail th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Fisher</hi> of his hopes; for <hi>Fish</hi> are the soone<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> stale of any thing, and a <hi>Pike</hi> may chance t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> catch at a stale <hi>Bait,</hi> and play with it briskly a<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> first, but it is great odds that he leaves it at last▪ if he be not extraordinarily pinched with hunger▪ A stale <hi>Bait</hi> (we acknowledge) may make a goo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> shift sometimes, but it must be neither in <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer,</hi> nor in <hi>Spawning-time,</hi> in <hi>October</hi> o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>April</hi> they are not so curious but they can di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>spense with an indifferent diet; and in col<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Weather a <hi>Bait</hi> may keep two or three days
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199384:27"/> and yet be very servicable, especially at <hi>Snap,</hi> which makes no difference in <hi>Baits</hi> as to the sense of tasting; if they look bright and glister in the water, it is not material whether they be old or new; which affords a greater variety of <hi>Baits</hi> then that of <hi>Pouch:</hi> any thing that may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the eye, may be used at <hi>Snap;</hi> some will take a piece of hard <hi>Cheese</hi> or <hi>Pack wax,</hi> a <hi>Rasher</hi> of <hi>Bacon</hi> or a <hi>Sheeps Gut,</hi> or almost any thing that is radient and shining; some will float on the top with a live <hi>Bird,</hi> a <hi>Swallow,</hi> or a <hi>Sparrow;</hi> though I judge that may be more out of curiosity, then for profit or sport. I never admired this way of <hi>Snap,</hi> as thinking it too quick and surprizing, to give any diversion; the sport of <hi>Trolling</hi> consisting more in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the <hi>Bite,</hi> in the playing of a <hi>Pike,</hi> and his eager biting and running with the <hi>Bait,</hi> then just a word and a blow, snapping him up and putting him into the Bag.</p>
               <p>One time of the year indeed, the <hi>Snap</hi> is the best means to attain the end, that is in <hi>March,</hi> when they are sick and about casting their <hi>Spawn;</hi> for then if your <hi>Snap-book</hi> be made the right way, with springs to strike sure, you may take four or five in the time the <hi>Pouch</hi> takes one: some fancy the <hi>Snap-hook</hi> plays the <hi>Bait</hi> more lively and naturally, though there may be no great difference, in that, especially if the <hi>Pouch-hook</hi> be fastened to the <hi>Line<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with a <hi>Swivel,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:199384:28"/> which is very conducible to the playing of a <hi>Bait.</hi> Some there are that <hi>Fish</hi> with their <hi>Baits</hi> alive, and have short <hi>Hooks</hi> fashioned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly with more joynts and without lead; but that is rather a destroying and a poching way, then any fair <hi>Fishing;</hi> it makes such a slaughter amongst the <hi>Fish,</hi> that it is not fit to be used: for I have known some <hi>Rivers</hi> that have been quickly eased of their burden of <hi>Fish</hi> by that unlawful trade: the way and method they use, is to lay it may be three or fourscore of these <hi>Hooks,</hi> which may reach almost a Mile, after they have lain four or five hours or more, or presently after they have done the last, they begin to take up the first; so that they will kill perhaps a score of <hi>Pikes</hi> and <hi>Jacks:</hi> which way (if allowable) is the ready course to empty a <hi>River,</hi> and engross all the sport to themselves; two or three at a time, or one, if considerable, is enough to content any mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Troller,</hi> that would have others partake of the Recreation as well as himself, and not fish above once or twice in a <hi>Season</hi> in the same place; for the means to preserve and continue this <hi>Sport,</hi> is to favour and cherish it: It is an easie matter indeed to take half a dozen or more, if he would stick at it a whole day in the beginning of the year, before the <hi>Waters</hi> are beaten or drag'd, for then they are so plentiful, that they shew themselves in every corner: As for a sweet and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199384:28"/> delicious <hi>Bait,</hi> a piece of an <hi>Eel</hi> may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd, which if once taken and tasted, a <hi>Pike</hi> will assuredly feed upon it; this may be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in <hi>Ponds</hi> and <hi>Stews,</hi> when they throw in <hi>Griggs</hi> to feed the <hi>Pikes.</hi> Of all the small <hi>Fish,</hi> a <hi>Perch</hi> makes the worst <hi>Bait,</hi> yet that may be used in a case of necessity, if you first cut off the fins and prickles on his back, though when you have done all you can at him, it will be but too little purpose; for a <hi>Perch</hi> is like a Prince among the <hi>Fish,</hi> and a <hi>Pik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is in so much fear of him, and hath that Antipathy against him, that he will much sooner fasten upon one of his own kind, then upon him; yet I have seen small <hi>Perches</hi> taken out of a <hi>Pikes</hi> belly, but it was in a <hi>Mote</hi> where he was kept short and had little else to feed upon; but if you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to this Bait, and can get no other to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote your sport, it is best to scrape off some of the <hi>Scales,</hi> for it being a dark Fish, it will make it look somwhat brighter, and still the <hi>Snap</hi> is the best <hi>Hook</hi> for it, because if the <hi>Scales</hi> of the <hi>Perch</hi> be on, a <hi>Pike</hi> cannot easily gorge or digest it. A small <hi>Jack</hi> is a far better <hi>Bait,</hi> though it seems unnatural, yet Fish are not bound to observe the Laws of Nature. If it be a foot long, it may be cut in two, and so made use of. A young <hi>Chub</hi> or a <hi>Shallow</hi> may be very useful, or any <hi>Fish</hi> that glisters and shines in the Water; a <hi>Bleak</hi> is a very bright
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199384:29"/> Fish. The way to keep and preserve your <hi>Baits</hi> till you have occasion to use them, is first to take a <hi>Cast Net</hi> and throw it, choosing those that are most fit for the purpose; and so lay them up in store: which must be done by having a Trunk ready to put them in, and then to take them out by two or three as occasion serves. In <hi>Summer</hi> time you may take them with an <hi>Angle,</hi> but that is very uncertain; nor can you have any choice that way, because they will often be too little or too big, besides it spends too much of the day that is intended for <hi>Trolling:</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you may take with one <hi>Bait</hi> fresh out of the <hi>Trunk,</hi> three or four <hi>Jacks</hi> or more; for a <hi>Fish</hi> that <hi>bites</hi> greedily and swallows the <hi>Bait,</hi> presently does not tear it so much, as one that plays with it in his mouth and then leaves it; for a <hi>Bait</hi> is not much worse for being chopt and full of holes, provided it hang well upon the <hi>Hook,</hi> and the <hi>lead</hi> is not seen; for one <hi>Pike</hi> will feed very well after another, and the <hi>Bait</hi> will be still the sweeter the more it is bitten, if it be not used so long to be water-sopt: the <hi>Scales</hi> of a <hi>Roch</hi> or <hi>Dace</hi> are a great preservation to it, as also light and perspicuous, which render it more visible to the eyes of the great devourer: As to the definite number of <hi>Baits,</hi> it cannot be positively determined; two or three if fresh, will last long enough, if you have not very ill luck with them; for sometimes the first <hi>Fish</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199384:29"/> that <hi>bites</hi> will tear the <hi>Bait:</hi> so that it will make it unserviceable, and yet not take the <hi>Pike,</hi> but the <hi>Weeds</hi> are most destructive to your <hi>Baits,</hi> especially when they are strong and tuff; so that if you be not careful in tying the tail of the <hi>Bait</hi> fast to the joynt of the <hi>Wire,</hi> the <hi>Weed</hi> will consume it, before the <hi>Pike</hi> comes. Some <hi>Fish</hi> will hold better than others; a <hi>Dace</hi> is one of the hardest, and will endure the longest; but a <hi>Gudgeon</hi> is but a tender <hi>Fish,</hi> and will soon burst: one fresh <hi>Bait</hi> will wear out two or three stale ones: Besides these natural <hi>Baits,</hi> there are a sort of Artificial ones, which are made so exquisitely to resemble the other, that they will delude the eyes of some Men, much more of the <hi>Fish;</hi> for if they be only look'd on, and not felt or touch'd with the finger, there is no doubt to be made of the reality of the <hi>Fish.</hi> Some pretend to <hi>Fish</hi> at <hi>Pouch</hi> with these Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial deceits, though 'tis more probable they were designed for the <hi>Snap;</hi> for a <hi>Pike</hi> is endued with a perfect sense of tasting, and therefore will scarce be courted to gorge and digest that which he can neither taste nor smell: There are indeed some of those Artificial <hi>Baits</hi> made after the <hi>Pouch</hi> fashion, whether for sight or service, to look upon rather then to use, I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; for I more admired the curiosity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity of the Artificer, then any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary excellency or usefulness in the thing. A
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199384:30"/>
                  <hi>Pike</hi> must be very hungry that gorges one of them, and he must do it hastily and greedily, for if he stays to consider of it and plays much with it, as some of them do, his curious and delicate <hi>Palate</hi> will presently distinguish a fresh and well relishing Morsel, from a dry and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipid bit.</p>
               <p>Those that are covetous, may have two strings to their bow; by taking a <hi>Gudgeon</hi> of a middle size or a large <hi>Minow,</hi> for then they may be in hopes of taking large <hi>Perches</hi> as well as <hi>Pikes,</hi> for a <hi>Minnow</hi> is an excellent <hi>Bait</hi> for a <hi>Perch;</hi> great <hi>Baits</hi> do most invite a <hi>Pike,</hi> but little ones are more secure to take him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the</hi> Pouch-Hook.</head>
               <p>OF <hi>Pike-Hooks</hi> or <hi>Jack-Hooks,</hi> there are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral sorts, both for the <hi>Snap</hi> and <hi>Pouch,</hi> the latter of which, we shall only endeavour to describe in this place; for though the <hi>Spring-Hooks</hi> are esteemed excellent, and strike sure, yet the ordinary plain <hi>Snap-Hook</hi> will miss al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most as often as it hits. Of <hi>Pouch-Hooks</hi> there are many fashions, some with a round bent, almost after the figure of a <hi>Perch-Hook;</hi> that may be very good, though I never made use of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199384:30"/> that fashion; for there is another sort which have a sloping bent outward, turning a little inwards under the beard, and withal bending the lead at the point of it, which point must be as sharp at it can be made; much after this fashion<figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of pouch hook</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>It is the best to choose them of a black and somewhat blewish colour, indifferent thick and strong, the lead not very gross, but neatly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, without any flaws or hollows in it, you may lead it your self if you buy them bare; by putting your <hi>Hook</hi> into a <hi>Reed,</hi> or a piece of <hi>Elder,</hi> or any such hollow thing; provided you do it fair and smooth, making it thicker in the middle or towards the bottom, then at the top, which must be narrow and slender. It will require an indifferent quantity of lead, for if it be pretty weighty, it plays the <hi>Bait</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; this is supposed of a single <hi>Hook,</hi> though the double one is the same as to the lead and joynts of the wire: I commonly made use of the single <hi>Hook,</hi> which strikes as sure as the other. The double <hi>Hook</hi> hath one advantage above the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199384:31"/> other, that if it meets with such resistance in the <hi>Water,</hi> that it loses one side of it, the other part with a little plaining and filing, may be still as serviceable as it was before; it is more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome in the <hi>Water,</hi> and more apt to check and take hold of the <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>Roots;</hi> it is the fittest for a great <hi>Bait,</hi> for if you put a small and slender <hi>Bait</hi> on a double <hi>Hook,</hi> it will hang out and bear off so much in the bendings, that a <hi>Pike</hi> may not only discover the delusion and craft of it, but if he chance to take it, it may check him in his feeding, and so hinder him from gorging of it: There are two or three sorts of double <hi>Hooks,</hi> besides that of the <hi>Snap,</hi> some of them are flat and are bent back to back, after this manner:<figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of double hook</figDesc>
                  </figure> Another sort there is that is more sloped and the bents closer together; others there are that have a round bent, much after the form of the <hi>Snap,</hi> which must always have a full bent, and very large; That is baited by fixing the <hi>Hook</hi> in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199384:31"/> the middle of the <hi>Bait,</hi> and may have the lead fastened to the <hi>Wire;</hi> the way to use that, is to strike soon after the <hi>Fish</hi> bite, and as the <hi>Pike</hi> runs one way to strike the contrary.</p>
               <p>In the choice of <hi>Hooks,</hi> you may have some regard to the <hi>Wire,</hi> lest that be rugged or knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for if that be not found and strong, you may lose both your <hi>Fish</hi> and your <hi>Hook.</hi> The first joynt of it which is next the <hi>Lead,</hi> must be so long that the tail of the <hi>Bait</hi> may not reach over it, for if it does, you cannot well fasten it to the joynt, though in a time of necessity you may untwist the wire of the upper joynt, and there fix the thred; some <hi>Baits</hi> are short, as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> and <hi>Shallows;</hi> some are longer, as <hi>Daces, Bleaks,</hi> or large <hi>Gudgeons,</hi> which require that the <hi>Hook</hi> and <hi>Wire</hi> be both long proportionable to it. The other joynt which is fastened to the <hi>Line,</hi> must be twice or thrice the length of the other; lest when the <hi>Pike</hi> hath gorged the <hi>Bait</hi> deep into his <hi>Ventricle,</hi> the <hi>Wire</hi> be not long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reach out of his mouth, and so he shear and cut the <hi>Line</hi> with his <hi>Teeth;</hi> this joynt had need be very fine and smooth, lest if it be rugged, it tear the <hi>Bait</hi> when you put it on; if this be stiff and strong, you need not that which they call the <hi>Arming Wire</hi> to help you thrust it out of the tail of the <hi>Bait;</hi> you may sometimes search your <hi>Wire,</hi> least it be faulty or broken, especially the lowest joynt, for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199384:32"/> there it often breaks, and may deceive you in your intended pastime.</p>
               <p>There are another sort of <hi>Hooks</hi> which are made purposely for the <hi>Ledger Baits;</hi> those are used with live <hi>Fish,</hi> and are not leaded, the <hi>Hook</hi> is rather shorter than the other, but the <hi>Wire</hi> hath usually more joynts. The <hi>Lines</hi> for these need not be so long as the <hi>Trolling Line,</hi> for they may be thrown into the <hi>Water,</hi> and so gaged with a stick; for a <hi>Pike</hi> will not so soon take a <hi>Bait</hi> off the ground, as if it swims a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a foot or more from the bottom. The way of <hi>Fishing</hi> with <hi>Ledger-Baits</hi> is too destructive to be made a common practice, and far below the diversions of a fair <hi>Fisherman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The best <hi>Hooks</hi> may be chosen by their <hi>Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> which is the hardest and best temper'd <hi>Steel;</hi> these are so well composed, that they break and snap, rather then stand bent, or be the least moved from their first frame and figure; there is much variety in <hi>Hooks,</hi> and a great deal of deceit in them, and therefore it requires skill and caution to choose the best.</p>
               <p>When you fasten the <hi>Wire</hi> to the <hi>Line,</hi> you must be sure to tie it with a right knot; least it catch a <hi>Weed</hi> that is far stronger then a <hi>Pike,</hi> and it slip the knot and get from you; but if all your <hi>Tackling</hi> be new and sound, you need not fear to adventure among <hi>Fog</hi> or <hi>Weeds,</hi> or any thing but <hi>Roots</hi> and <hi>Stumps</hi> of <hi>Trees,</hi> which may
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199384:32"/> hold play with a <hi>Cart-Rope.</hi> To this end the safest and most secure way of fastening, is first to tie one single knot, and then one that will slip, or else only the slipping not, allowing it an inch or two of <hi>Line,</hi> and then girding and drawing it close, first making tryal of it with all your strength before you put it into the <hi>Water</hi> it's a neat and handsome way to fasten it with a <hi>Swivel,</hi> tying it close with a bit of Thred; this seems to play the Bait better, giving it a turn when you stir it, which makes it glister and swim like a live <hi>Fish.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are a sort of course <hi>Hooks</hi> made of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> and thick <hi>Wire,</hi> which may make a shift to serve those that can get no better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of the</hi> Trolling Line.</head>
               <p>NOw as to the Line it self, it is one of the chiefest and most necessary <hi>Member</hi> that is required to the Constitution of the body of a <hi>Fisherman:</hi> for an ordinary and indifferent <hi>Hook</hi> may be sometimes dispenc'd withal to shew good sport, as also the <hi>Pole;</hi> but if your <hi>Line</hi> be not strong and of a considerable length, you can have but little hopes of any competent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199384:33"/> success: The best materials for the composure of your <hi>Line,</hi> is green or blew <hi>Silk,</hi> which <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulcan</hi> colour is most resembling and agreeable to the <hi>Water;</hi> but it is possible it may be only a fancy that that colour is of more consequence than another; yet sometimes the pleasing of the fancy, does so much enliven and encourage the <hi>Fisherman,</hi> that it makes him the more active and laborious, and so by that means is the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of all his sport; and if his fancy divert him another way, he will take the less care and pains in his present pastime.</p>
               <p>Next to <hi>Silk,</hi> the best sort of green <hi>Thred</hi> is to be preferred, which though it be neither so handsome or so durable as <hi>Silk,</hi> yet it may last very strongly a year or two: but that wears like other things, according to the care and good keeping of the user; for if it be laid up wet, and on an heap, as soon as you have done <hi>Fishing,</hi> and take no more care of it, you may haply rot out as many <hi>Lines</hi> as you catch <hi>Pikes:</hi> The best way then of preserving it, is to wax it sometimes with <hi>Bees-wax,</hi> and when it is wet to wind it up loosly in long foldings, that the Air may come in to dry it, or else let it dry at length, and then wind it upon a Roll: with such usage, a <hi>Silk Line</hi> will last beyond your expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>There are some that make their <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>Sheep</hi> or <hi>Cats</hi> Guts; but I cannot conceive they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199384:33"/> are so suitable and agreeable to the <hi>Water</hi> as <hi>Silk,</hi> or <hi>Thred; Silk</hi> and <hi>Hair</hi> may be fitly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in the making of a <hi>Line;</hi> some make them of <hi>Silk</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> thinking that way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve it; tho the addition of <hi>Silver</hi> may be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to please their fancy and the gaity of their humour, then to keep their <hi>Line</hi> from perishing; such as they should have <hi>Silver Hooks</hi> to their <hi>Silver Lines,</hi> that if it cannot take <hi>Fish</hi> it self in the Water, it may take them ready caught, and so be useful in saving their credit.</p>
               <p>There are other sorts of course <hi>Lines</hi> very short, not above half the length of the <hi>Trolling Line,</hi> which are either to Fish with a <hi>Ledger-Bait,</hi> or to lie all night, being tyed to a Float, and cast into the water.</p>
               <p>These are not made of such fine stuff, neither are so well twisted as the other, and only serves in some exigencies, as when a <hi>Pike</hi> that will not be invited by <hi>Trolling,</hi> may be better pleased with a <hi>Bait</hi> that is laid for him: he will some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times so humble himself as to take it off the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; but it is the wiser course to tie a stick or a cork to the <hi>Line,</hi> that it may hang about a foot or more from the ground, observing the Wind withal, for if you throw it in against the Wind, it will drive it backwards, and carry the <hi>Bait</hi> close to the side, and though a <hi>Pike</hi> often har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours by the side, yet the middle hath more scope and advantage of drawing him to it; for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199384:34"/> these laying <hi>Lines</hi> the worst sort will serve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the lying so long in the Water is the ready way to rot them.</p>
               <p>As to the length of the <hi>Line,</hi> it is good to have enough, and far better to leave than to lack; for though a short <hi>Line</hi> may do very well in a <hi>Brook</hi> or some narrow place, where the <hi>Pike</hi> must either run upwards or downwards, and so you may follow your sport, yet if you come to a broad Reach, where the <hi>Fish</hi> run cross the <hi>Stream</hi> to the far side, you may often miss of your <hi>Pike</hi> for want of a few yards of <hi>Line;</hi> for if he be the least curb'd or stopt in his so speedy Career, and may not have his full swing, he is presently check'd, and leaves his suspicious prey. This I have often found by experience, though my <hi>Line</hi> was long enough, yet having a knot in it that would not quickly pass, as also being so entangled that it much shortened it, I have by that means lost very good <hi>Fish.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the precise length of it, that need not be determined, about 30 yards is a good <hi>medium</hi> for the <hi>Pouch,</hi> I cannot see any reason why it need be so long at <hi>Snap,</hi> for though they may throw out as far at <hi>Snap,</hi> yet that strikes as soon as he <hi>bites,</hi> and lets him run no farther, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as at <hi>Pouch</hi> he may go farther with it still, though it be far cast.</p>
               <p>It's true that for the <hi>Line</hi> at <hi>Snap</hi> ought to be thicker and stronger, for a sudden jerk may
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199384:34"/> break that which might hold a good pull by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; but as to the length, it need not be so long, because that is only for casting in, and a <hi>Pike</hi> will sometimes run farther with it then it can be thrown: so that I have seen those that have fish'd at <hi>Snap,</hi> with no longer a <hi>Line</hi> then what was tyed to the <hi>Pole,</hi> and so cast it up and down like an <hi>Angle:</hi> this was too short to be confin'd to no more <hi>Line</hi> then what was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Pole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the managing of the <hi>Line</hi> and fitting it for your sport, you may wind it upon a <hi>Roll</hi> that turns upon a ring of <hi>Iron</hi> with your finger in it, having no more in your hand then you make use of at the present: so that if occasion be, you may unwind it at your lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
               <p>Some draw it after them at length, which I approve as a very good way; if there be no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments in the way; as <hi>Shrubs</hi> or <hi>Bushes</hi> to interrupt or make them go back; it will be very ready to cast out, and may throw it the farthest; for if you hold a great deal loose in your hand, it will be apt to knot and tangle, which will try the <hi>Fishermans</hi> patience. Some object that the drawing the <hi>Line</hi> upon the ground will be apt to wear it out sooner, but that is questionable, for it sooner dries so, and when it is dry, it can take but little harm: besides a <hi>Pike</hi> will sometimes be so hasty and furious, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199384:35"/> he will scarce give you leave to unwind fast e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for him, and therefore the surest way to trapan him, is to make preparation for him, by having your <hi>Line</hi> at command in a compleat readiness.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the</hi> Pole.</head>
               <p>SUpposing your <hi>Hook</hi> be good, and your <hi>Line</hi> strong, you may make the better shift with an indifferent <hi>Pole;</hi> though some that are more curious in their <hi>Tackling</hi> than painful and patient in their <hi>Fishing,</hi> will not stir a foot without all the formalities of an exquisite <hi>Fisherman:</hi> such precise Crafts-Masters as these, can spend their time in admiring their <hi>Instruments,</hi> and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently delight themselves with the commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own <hi>Materials.</hi> This is certain and undeniable, that the longer the <hi>Pole</hi> is, if it be streight and light, you will find the more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in playing the <hi>Bait</hi> and throwing it from you; for if there be <hi>Flags</hi> or <hi>Reed</hi> between the <hi>Bank</hi> and the main <hi>deep,</hi> you can very hardly play your <hi>Bait</hi> with a short <hi>Pole.</hi> I confess I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten put a <hi>Ring</hi> upon my <hi>Hand-stick</hi> and made use of that instead of a <hi>Rod,</hi> and have had the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199384:35"/> fortune sometimes to take a <hi>Pike</hi> well nigh as long as my <hi>Pole:</hi> sometimes I have taken nothing with me, but confided in the <hi>Willows</hi> that grew next to the place designed for that days Recreation, cutting down as good a Stick as I could find, and so making a bent at the end for the <hi>Line</hi> to slip; and have left it at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the Sport: In a broad River or a Pond, being at a pinch, I have had no <hi>Pole</hi> at all, but only took the <hi>Bait</hi> in my hand, and cast it from me like a stone to the length of my <hi>Line,</hi> the end of which I was sure to fasten about me, least I threw it quite out, and then have repented of my folly when it was too late to amend it. In some places they fish altogether that way where the <hi>River</hi> is deep and clear from <hi>Weeds.</hi> I never accustomed my self to a long <hi>Pole,</hi> lest I might seem like them that make a great bustle, and take but few <hi>Fish.</hi> I generally made use of an <hi>Alder</hi> as long as I could get, commonly about three yards long, which I bark'd and kept dry for lightness and easie carriage; when it was throughly dry it would be tough, and so light, that I could scarce feel it in my hand; and there is no objection to be made, that such a stick is too weak; for any thing is strong enough at <hi>Pouch</hi> that will play the <hi>Bait</hi> and throw it from you; there is no weight or stress upon the <hi>Pole,</hi> and but little upon the <hi>Line;</hi> if you strike the <hi>Fish</hi> gently and play him slightly and dexterou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199384:36"/> you may tire him with a slender <hi>Line,</hi> if it be long and can keep him from <hi>Weeds</hi> and <hi>Roots;</hi> at <hi>Snap</hi> indeed your <hi>Tackling</hi> must be all fitted accordingly, your <hi>Line</hi> very strong, and your <hi>Pole</hi> on purpose of a good <hi>Ash,</hi> or <hi>Withy,</hi> or <hi>Hazel</hi> well dryed; streight and tuff, that it may be able to draw him out <hi>nolens volens,</hi> by meer force and compulsion: He that uses that way is scarce a word and a blow, for the mistaken <hi>Fish</hi> no sooner lays his Mouth upon the deceitful <hi>Bait,</hi> but he is catch'd up into another Element. The way of <hi>Pouch</hi> is far more mild and flattering, though as much destructive and pernicious. If you use an <hi>Ash</hi> or an <hi>Hazel Pole,</hi> you must have a <hi>Ring</hi> fixed at the end, some have two; that is one in the middle, though I see no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of that superfluity. If it be an <hi>Alder</hi> or a <hi>Cane,</hi> or any hollow Wood, you may have an <hi>Iron Ring</hi> made to screw in at the top about an handful or more in length, or else that which may be at well, a piece of dry <hi>Alder</hi> that is cut sharp and sloping about three or four Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es long, which you may stick fast in the end of the <hi>Pole;</hi> some have only a Ring with a little Screw very short. If your <hi>Pole</hi> be of <hi>Alder,</hi> it will be apt to crack, you may secure that by binding the end of it hard with a Waxed Thred, and then you may thrust in at the top without any danger of breaking or cleaving the <hi>Pole.</hi> A dry <hi>Withy</hi> or <hi>Hazel,</hi> bored about twelve or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199384:36"/> Foot, will make an excellent <hi>Pole;</hi> which may serve for <hi>Angling</hi> if it be so long, only put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a top into it, as also at <hi>Snap.</hi> It is a great ease to have a light <hi>Pole,</hi> and therefore the best course is to get them in the season of the year, and let them stand near the Fire, or in some dry place, for the space of half a year or more; for if your Rod be green and heavy, it will make you weary of your Sport, and be a great hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and discouragement to your <hi>Fishing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is, if sport be quick and good, scarce any thing can vex or discompose the <hi>Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> for he is then so attentive on his pleasure, that he takes little notice of those inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which otherwise might be a trouble and vexation to him; he then regards neither Wind nor Weather, and disdains those slight pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations of Cold, Thirst, or Hunger; he hath then gotten the <hi>Philosophers</hi> Stone which sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens all his other crosses, and turns all disasters into Gold. His Sport is a Cordial for all his Distempers, and the <hi>Pike</hi> (like a good <hi>Water-Physician</hi>) can cure him of all his Diseases: if he be weary, his sport refreshes him, if cold, it warms him; if melancholly, it cheers him; if drowsie, it revives him; if in pain, it eases him; if sick, it recovers him: he then fee's not the weight of his <hi>Pole,</hi> nor is concern'd that his <hi>Tackling</hi> is no better. This is the prosperity of the <hi>Fisher,</hi> but if you see him in adversity,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199384:37"/> when fortune does not smile on his endeavours, you shall, find him much altered, and in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary condition; supposing (I say) the thing called <hi>Luck</hi> does not attend him, and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Sport does not sweeten all other Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, which should refine all the dross of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward misfortunes, he it then so much at a loss and dejected, that he can expect but a bitter potion: Patience and Hopes are the tw<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> chiefest Pillars that support the Building of<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Fisherman;</hi> for if they be once disturbed or sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, you may easily foresee the ruins of <hi>Pisca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you desire to be private at your Sport, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to go undiscovered to the <hi>River,</hi> you ma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> walk out with an <hi>Oak</hi> stick or the like in you<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hand, taking a Ring with a Screw at it; yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> may deceive the expectations of others, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pass on without the least suspicion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> How to Bait the <hi>Hook,</hi> and to play the <hi>Bait.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough it be supposed that you are perfectl<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> furnish'd with all sorts of Tools and Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are required to the making up th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> very Essence of a <hi>Fisherman,</hi> and that you ar<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199384:37"/> as throughly accoutred with all the Materials and Utensils for <hi>Fishing</hi> as <hi>Piscator</hi> himself could possibly be, yet if you know not how to use these Implements, you will be soon weary of your Sport, and despair of learning the <hi>Art of Trolling;</hi> provided then that your <hi>Baits</hi> are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, take a couple of <hi>Hooks</hi> at least with you; if you have a mind, you may <hi>Bait</hi> them before you set out, especially if the Weather be cold, that it may not trespass too much upon your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience when you come to the <hi>River:</hi> The way then to <hi>Bait</hi> your <hi>Hook,</hi> is first to thrust your Wire into the mouth of the <hi>Fish,</hi> quite through the belly and out at the tail; some have besides the running Wire a Knitting Needle on purpose, but if the first joynt of your Wire be stiff and strong, it may very well be done with that; the point of the <hi>Hook</hi> must be even with the belly of the <hi>Bait;</hi> for if it hang on either side, it may hinder and check the <hi>Pike,</hi> who will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably lay his mouth upon it; for when he chops cross the <hi>Fish,</hi> he may be pricked, and so leave you only the hopes of another <hi>Bite;</hi> when you have so put through the <hi>Fish,</hi> then tie the Tail of the <hi>Bait</hi> fast to the joynt of the Wire with strong Thred, which will both make it hang streight upon the <hi>Hook,</hi> and preserve it from outward violences; for if it be not well fastened, the Weeds will have so much power over it, that they will soon tear it down to the Gills, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199384:38"/> so separate the <hi>Hook</hi> from the <hi>Bait;</hi> some fasten it with a Needle.</p>
               <p>The best way of fixing your <hi>Hook</hi> to the <hi>Line,</hi> is with a <hi>Swivel,</hi> which if you have not, you may make it fast with one slipping knot, which you may untie without cutting your <hi>Line.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you are thus fixed for your intended Sport, then drop in your <hi>Bait</hi> first even before you, then cast it on each side to search them, and let the third throw be before you into the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, afterwards cast about all places where you conceive your Game lies, or any where that you can fish without annoyance; for a <hi>Pike</hi> often delights himself in a very unlikely and improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Harbour; and therefore the surest way to meet with him, is to fish true and close; mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing as little of the River as you can: which though it be tedious, yet it is the only way to search and see what store of <hi>Fish</hi> a <hi>River</hi> afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and you may often have a <hi>Bite,</hi> when you think least of it.</p>
               <p>Now the farther you throw in your <hi>Bait,</hi> the more advantage you gain by it, and more hopes of a Bite, provided there be no impediments is your way, as <hi>Weeds, Roots,</hi> or the like; fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> if the place be foul or weedy, you canno<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> make out so far, but only drop in your <hi>Bai<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> here and there by the sides and in holes that an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> clear and deep: The Weeds are bad Enemie<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:199384:38"/> to the <hi>Bait</hi> and <hi>Hook;</hi> though a good <hi>Hook</hi> and a <hi>Line</hi> answerable to it, will pull up the strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of them; for I cannot remember that I ever lost a <hi>Hook</hi> by a <hi>Weed</hi> alone, except it had some stump or root of a Tree to be assistant to it; the <hi>Candocks</hi> indeed, and <hi>Bullrushes</hi> will much disfigure and annoy your <hi>Bait,</hi> and almost quite discountenance a young Undertaker; for if the smallest bit of weed hang upon the <hi>Hook,</hi> a <hi>Pike</hi> will be very sqeamish to gorge it; though some affirm that he feeds upon a Weed one time of the year, which they call from thence <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerill Weed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Supposing then that you have cast out a very fair throw, it may be a dozen or sometimes twenty yards, which may easily be done if the <hi>River</hi> requires it; let it first have a little time to sink, then feel it, and draw it gently towards you; for a <hi>Pike</hi> often takes it at the first sight before it gets to the bottom, and if you snatch it hastily, you may chance to give him such a discouragement, that you may be deprived of your expected sport: after you have given it an easie motion towards you, let it have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of sinking again, then draw it slowly and softly, for if you jerk it too quick and hastily, you will not give him leave to lay hold upon the <hi>Bait;</hi> for he will often shoot himself from the farthest sides, and at a great distance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so quick sighted in the Water: when you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199384:39"/> have got your <hi>Bait</hi> near the Bank, then play it longer there; first deep: for the deeper you <hi>Fish</hi> the better, especially in cold Weather; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards raise it higher and higher by degrees till you see it, and then you may often have the pleasure of being an Eye-Witness to your own <hi>bite;</hi> and though you have before been often deceived in your hopes, and have caught a Weed instead of a Fish, yet now you may as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure your self, if the Proverb hold true, <hi>That seeing is believing:</hi> there are indeed some sort of Weeds, and the stream together, which may often give encouragements, by promising Sport, and performing none; they will some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times so exactly imitate a real <hi>Bite,</hi> that an old and experienced <hi>Fisherman</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be mistaken with all his craft and cunning. The best way then to be sure, is to pull your <hi>Line</hi> gently till you come to feel it, and if it be a <hi>Fish,</hi> the moving of the <hi>Bait,</hi> will make him more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and greedy, he will then strike out and gorge it; whereas if he lay still and not stirr'd, he would very probably leave it. When you have raised your <hi>Bait</hi> so high towards the top, it may be within two or three foot, that you can perceive it to glister; you may then comfort your self with the hopes of a <hi>Pike</hi> that may rise at it, as he often does, and therefore it is not prudence to bee too hasty in taking out the <hi>Bite.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:199384:39"/>
               <p>When a <hi>Pike</hi> is once stirr'd, he will lie as it were watching for the <hi>Bait,</hi> and catch gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily at it, if he does not see you; therefore you must be careful to keep a little distance upon the <hi>Bank,</hi> for they will often take it at the very top, and sometimes leap out of the Water at it; but they are then commonly so much affrighted that they will not be courted to <hi>Bite</hi> any more; you may <hi>Fish</hi> as close as you will, though it be not material whether you throw two or three times in one and the same place; for he is so hungry, that he usually imbraces the first op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to lay hold upon his Feed.</p>
               <p>Some there are that <hi>Troll</hi> with great <hi>Corks</hi> and <hi>Floats</hi> on their <hi>Line,</hi> which may do the best with the <hi>Ledger-Bait,</hi> though I never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of that way; for the Weeds will make the Flote dance as exactly as a <hi>Pike,</hi> except he bite very greedily, and so you may often be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in your expectation; sometimes I grant, you may distinguish and be sensible of your <hi>Bite</hi> if he runs with it, and especially up the Stream; but if he goes downwards and <hi>bites</hi> slowly, you cannot assure your self whether it be a <hi>Fish</hi> or a <hi>Weed.</hi> If a place be free from <hi>Weeds,</hi> you may make the best shift with a <hi>Cork;</hi> though you may be often mistaken when you lay a little too deep; for the <hi>Hook</hi> will draw along the bottom, and you will be ready to comfort your self with the hopes of Sport.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199384:40"/>
               <p>In some places they <hi>Troll</hi> without any <hi>Pole</hi> or any playing of the <hi>Bait,</hi> as I have seen them throw a <hi>Line</hi> out of a <hi>Boat,</hi> and so let it draw af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them as they Row forward; but that must needs be a careless and unsafe way, for though they may have <hi>Bites</hi> and <hi>Offers</hi> so, yet it must certainly check the <hi>Fish</hi> so much that he will never Pouch it; I cannot tell what Art they may have at the <hi>Snap,</hi> though it is very improbable to have any as they go to work, without either <hi>Pole</hi> or <hi>Stick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now besides them that are not indued with that excellent gift of <hi>Patience,</hi> there are some of our young Pretenders that have too much confidence or rather too little skill; these will stand an hour or two in one place, as immova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the Trees they stand by, they are so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate with the <hi>Fish,</hi> that they would force them to bite; and if there be never a <hi>Pike</hi> in the place where they are, they do their endeavou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to wait till one comes: these are indefatigable Crafts-men, which can weary the <hi>Fish</hi> soone<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> than themselves, and are neither discourage<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with ill fortune, nor transported vvit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> good.</p>
               <p>As to the baiting the <hi>Hook</hi> with a <hi>Frog,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> spoke nothing, because I never made that an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> part of my practice; s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me <hi>Frogs</hi> are though<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to be venemous, as the <hi>Land Frog,</hi> or that whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> breeds by Land; it is observ'd by some, that<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:199384:40"/>
                  <hi>Pike</hi> hath an Antipathy against this. And of these there are several sorts, some speckled, some greenish, which are the most dangerous to touch; these breed by flime and dust of the Earth, which turn to slime in <hi>Winter;</hi> and in <hi>Summer</hi> to a living Creature again. <hi>Cardan</hi> gives a reason for the raining of <hi>Frogs,</hi> which proceed from putrefaction, and are not supposed to be that sort of <hi>Frogs</hi> which engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>February</hi> or <hi>March,</hi> and breed in Ditches by slime and blackish Eggs. If you intend to <hi>Troll</hi> with a <hi>Frog,</hi> you must choose out of these the yellowest you can get; first then put your <hi>Hook</hi> into his Mouth, which you may do from <hi>May</hi> day to the end of <hi>August,</hi> afterwards some say his Mouth grows up, and so con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inues at least six Months without eating, and is su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stained, no one knows how (but the great Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.) Put in the arming <hi>Wyre</hi> in at his Mouth, and out at his <hi>Gills,</hi> and then with a fine <hi>Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> and <hi>Silk</hi> sow the upper part of his Leg, with only one stitch to the arming <hi>Wyre,</hi> or tye the Frogs Leg to the upper joynt of the <hi>Wire;</hi> use him gently and he will live the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: when you have thus baited it, you may fasten your <hi>Line</hi> to a bough, a bunch of <hi>flags,</hi> or a bundle of straw, and by the help of the wind they will more cross a <hi>Pond</hi> or <hi>Mere.</hi> Some will tye four or five live Baits to <hi>Bladders,</hi> and let them swim down the River, whilst they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199384:41"/> walk softly a long the shore. Others will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten baits to <hi>Ducks</hi> or <hi>Geese,</hi> and so let them swim about the <hi>Pond;</hi> if there be store of <hi>Pikes</hi> you may see excellent sport this way, for some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a great <hi>Pike</hi> will draw the <hi>Duck</hi> under the Water. This is the most proper to <hi>Fish</hi> with live <hi>Baits,</hi> and so to gage your <hi>Line</hi> with a Forked stick, with a nick or notch at one end of it, and put in <hi>Line</hi> enough for him to have his full liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Pouching.</hi> This is the ordinary way of <hi>Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> after that manner, if you have none of the fore-spoken things to move your <hi>Bait.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> How to strike a <hi>Pike</hi> and land him.</head>
               <p>WHen you have diverted your self as long as you think good with the pleasure of a <hi>Bite,</hi> and can guess by the running of the <hi>Pike,</hi> what progress he hath made in his repaste, by his ranging about for more; you may then hook him with a small jerk, and so take your fill of your contented sport: for though vve say of a <hi>Pike</hi> as of a Thief, give him Rope enough and he will hang himself, yet a fine gentle stroak will do no harm, but rather secure him, and entangle him the faster: supposing then that he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199384:41"/> hath fed a little, you may observe what moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he makes. If he takes the <hi>Bait</hi> greedily at bottom, and marches up the Stream with it, or strikes cross the <hi>River</hi> towards his hold, he will then probably lie still a little time, while he is <hi>Pouching,</hi> as you may feel him check and tug at it; from which place if he goes quick, you may let him alone a little longer, for you may come to lose all for want of two or three minutes forbearance: if he hath lain still a while the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time and then runs with it, you may let him go with it still, if you have a desire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Sport; if not, you may draw your <hi>Line</hi> streight, and with your <hi>Pole</hi> give him an easie stroke, and so feel him by degrees, till you come to see him; but if he makes much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance and is very furious, let him have <hi>Line</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and give him his full swing: he will be very angry at first, till he is better pacified by losing of his strength.</p>
               <p>As soon as you strike him, you may conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of what bigness he is, for if he be large you will find him strong and unruly in the Water; but if small and light, you can scarce tell whether you have any thing or not, or perhaps he may (for madness) leap out of the Water as soon as he is prick'd; but if he be a good one, at (I say) you may either see or feel him: you must be very cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and take a great deal of care and diligence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199384:42"/> in getting him to shore; for if the River be broad and your <hi>Line</hi> short, you may very well lose him; for he will launch out with that extremity and violence, that though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not break the <hi>Line,</hi> yet he vvill tear his ovvn Entrails, if he be there hung.</p>
               <p>Novv if a <hi>Fish</hi> takes your Bait at the top of the Water, and runs fiercely with it into the deep, and there lies still for some time, and you perceive that he does not <hi>Pouch</hi> it, your remedy for that is to stir him a little, to make him run and be more eager of it; then after he hath lain still and runs vvith it again, there is no great danger of losing that fish; for vvhen they leave it they commonly throvv it up at their first stage, that is the first time they lie still. Sometimes he will take it again after he hath left it, and run to his hold and play with it more than he did at first, shewing very good sport for a while, and and after all leave you in the lurch. A <hi>fish</hi> that takes it most greedily at the beginning, and carries it the furthest, does notwithstanding often forsake it; for as the proverb says, <hi>Nil violentum est diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnum.</hi> So a <hi>Pike</hi> that bites so eagerly at first, is too fierce to last; for it happens that he often leaves it: the only way to be even with such a <hi>Fish,</hi> is to take the Snap, and that may chance to stop his career.</p>
               <p>Now when you have a Bite, and the <hi>Fish</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:199384:42"/> goes down the Stream with it, we are apt to conceive it is a small <hi>Jack;</hi> but on the contrary, if he sails slowly upwards with the <hi>Bait,</hi> it is a sign of a good one; for the greater sort bite more calmly and moderately than the less; for they snatch, and away with it without any care or deliberation: Old <hi>Fish</hi> are more wary and cunning, they are sooner taken with a <hi>Line</hi> laid for them all night, then by <hi>Trolling.</hi> It is something difficult to know of what size a <hi>Pike</hi> is, before he is <hi>Stricken,</hi> and therefore there's none but may be mistaken in their Conjectures; for an indifferent <hi>Fish,</hi> I mean about 20 or 22 Inches, will often make as good Sport as one twice as big, however before you strike him; but then generally the bigger the <hi>Pike</hi> is, the more delightful will the Sport be. Sometimes he will take the <hi>Bait</hi> very hastily, and run out to the length of your <hi>Line,</hi> and never lie still at all, but all along he will play up and down with it, till you think fit to strike him.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Water</hi> is clear and not very deep, you may see him rise at it and take it; so you may see the <hi>Bait</hi> glister as it lies cross his mouth; you may then see when he hath <hi>Pouch'd,</hi> and know your time to strike.</p>
               <p>When you have first stricken him, you must be sure to have your <hi>Line</hi> ready and slack, that he may take as much liberty as he will; for when
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199384:43"/> he finds himself gull'd, and trapan'd with the <hi>Hook,</hi> he will use all his might and cunning to give you the lose. As you feel him come easily towards you, you may be still drawing, till you feel him make resistance again, then you may let him have his swing, till the heat of his fury is over, then gather your <hi>Line</hi> to you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, till he starts away, and if you can get him to the top, it will the sooner tire him; for the more he strives and throws himself from you the sooner he will be weary; after this manner by drawing him up and letting him loose again, you may tire him and tame him, till you bring him to your hand, and then he will lie so quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if the Hook was out, he could scarce strike off and get away.</p>
               <p>If you have hung him in the <hi>Gills,</hi> you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lose him, though you pull him out by meer force and violence, but if it hang loosely either in his <hi>Gorge</hi> or his <hi>Throat,</hi> he may deceive you, though he destroys himself, leaving you part of his <hi>Guts</hi> on the <hi>Hook</hi> for a <hi>Legacy,</hi> and dying soon after of his received Wounds. When you have after all this divertisement brought him to the <hi>Bank,</hi> you will find something to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can confidently call him your own; for if you go unadvisedly to take him out, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Back</hi> or the <hi>Tail,</hi> or any part of his <hi>Body,</hi> though you think his best is past, and his dancing days are done, yet he may cut yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199384:43"/> another Capor; and if he has had a little breathing time, he may give another leap, when you do not expect it; the best way then, is to use fair means, and invite to the land by perswasions, not compulsions, taking him by the <hi>Head,</hi> and putting your fingers into his <hi>Eyes,</hi> which is the fastest hold. If the <hi>Water</hi> be low, so that the <hi>Bank</hi> rises some distance from it; you must not fear catching an <hi>Ague,</hi> by laying your <hi>Belly</hi> level with the ground, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if you have no contrivance to guide him outwards to a more commodious place: some will adventure to take him by the <hi>Gills,</hi> though <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hat hold is neither so secure nor so safe for the <hi>Fisher;</hi> because the <hi>Fish</hi> in that heat of passion, may accidentally take revenge upon his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, by letting him blood in his Fingers, which way of Phlebotomizing is not esteemed so good, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ecause some are of opinion, that the <hi>Teeth</hi> of a <hi>Pike</hi> are Venemous, and those Wounds very <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ifficult to be healed.</p>
               <p>If there be <hi>Reeds</hi> and <hi>Shallows</hi> between you <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nd the deep, or if the <hi>River</hi> be in that <hi>Ebbe</hi> that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ou cannot reach him to lay hands on him, you <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ust contrive some other means to conduct him <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a more convenient landing. You may have <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Eye of that when you first strike him, looking <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pwards and downwards, and forecasting for <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>our best advantage: but if it be all along so <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eedy (as it is commonly in <hi>Ponds</hi> or <hi>Meres</hi>)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:199384:44"/> that it will be so prejudical to your Sport, that you can have no conveniency of his safe arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, by bringing him to your hand, you must then be content with the hopes of success, by committing your self unto the hands of fortune, having nothing to trust to at that juncture of time, but that which you may call the <hi>Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> luck. If you have as well debilitated his strength as tired his patience, you may proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly draw him out with no great reluctancy; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially if the <hi>Weeds</hi> be not so strong and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their Watry Element, that they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselves to part the fray between the <hi>Fish</hi> and the <hi>Fisher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Those that are more nice and curious, then painful and industrious, have their Net ready by them, least their stooping might be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous unto them: this Net (I suppose) is made in the fashion of a little <hi>Sparrow Net,</hi> with a long Trail, and a Pole at it, to translate Mr. <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> out of his own into the Airy Element.</p>
               <p>This is a very quaint and delicate way of <hi>Trol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> such as use it must have their Attendants to assist them; that as the <hi>Philosopher</hi> said, <hi>Omnia mea mecum Porto.</hi> So they will have their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitors to carry their Implements and Tools after them; these are of more power on Shore, then in the Water, and have more Authority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their retinue by the Land, than the Fish in the Waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:199384:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> How to preserve a River for <hi>Trolling.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe way and means to preserve a <hi>River</hi> for your own Sport, is to secure it from all those Enemies that are hurtful and destructive to it. The first and greatest, which may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Arch-Enemy,</hi> is the <hi>Drag,</hi> which is as unmerciful as an Epidemical Disease, that sweeps all into the dust; or as a greedy and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous <hi>Monopolizer,</hi> engrosseth all into its own possessions, and so verifies the old Proverb, That all are <hi>Fish</hi> that come to that Net. Some there are that commend the following of the <hi>Drag</hi> to <hi>Troll</hi> immediately after it; these love to fish in troubled Waters, for they say, The Dragging the River, stirs up the <hi>Fish</hi> and makes them more ready to catch at their prey: I cannot applaud the practice of these, nor judge it any ways consentaneous to reason; for though it be confess'd that its an hard Battel where none escapes, and that the <hi>Drag</hi> like an Universal Distemper cuts off the major part, yet still there will be some left to renew their Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which after a short time of quiet and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance will multiply and replenish the <hi>Waters.</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:199384:45"/> This I suppose, if there was none to come in and succeed them in their place, as there are continually; though (I say) they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose these ends as encouragements to their Sport, yet they will find such a scarcity and diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the <hi>Fish,</hi> that their pastime will be very cold and uncomfortable, having nothing to hope for or trust unto but those few <hi>Scape-Drags,</hi> which are only as the Gleanings when the Harvest is gone.</p>
               <p>Another Enemy to the Sport is the <hi>Bow-Net,</hi> which though it be far more favourable and sparing, and of a far lower Classis than the <hi>Drag,</hi> yet it is by so much the more dangerous by how much it is private and undiscovered; for the <hi>Drag</hi> is a profess'd and a publick Foe, which gives some notice and intimation to avoid those places it hath lately cleansed; but the <hi>Bow Net</hi> is so close and secret a Murtherer, that it cunningly slays and leaves no visible Wound.</p>
               <p>Another Plea there is that may be alledged for the <hi>Drag,</hi> which is this, that it is seldom used above once, sometimes not so often as once by the year; but the <hi>Bow-Net</hi> kills and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroys, spoils and plunders all the year long; the Spring time indeed is the fittest for it, when the <hi>Fish</hi> run and get into the <hi>Scoures;</hi> or else im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after a <hi>Flood;</hi> to lay many of these in small Rivulets and Ditches, they that use them,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199384:45"/> may then make their Harvest of them, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after a <hi>Spring-flood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Enemy that presents it self to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of for avoiding, is the <hi>Stall</hi> or <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel:</hi> a Net which is made up of great <hi>Mashes,</hi> as it is so much the more tolerable and allowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, because it holds only the great <hi>Fish,</hi> and gives the lesser leave to escape. This <hi>Net</hi> is not so common, nor so much to be condemn'd as the <hi>Bow-Net,</hi> because it is usually assisting to the <hi>Drag.</hi> In <hi>Washes</hi> and back <hi>Dikes</hi> it may do good service, because there they may both draw it, and plunge on both sides it; but in the main <hi>River</hi> it can do no great Execution, but only set as a <hi>Stall</hi> to stop the <hi>Fish:</hi> In one respect it is very Murdering, because the <hi>Mashes</hi> are made so alike on both sides, that it takes the <hi>Fish</hi> which way soever they come. They that use this Sport, have commonly two to set at a little distance, and then they may meet, and take most that are between them.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Cast-Net,</hi> it is rather a Friend and subservient to the <hi>Troll,</hi> than an Enemy to the <hi>Sport:</hi> for there is no way so good to take <hi>Baits</hi> as with that; because out of a multitude of <hi>Fish</hi> which it takes, you may have your choice of <hi>Baits.</hi> An <hi>Angle</hi> indeed may make a shift some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in <hi>Summer,</hi> but that often takes either those that are too little or too big for <hi>Baits.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199384:46"/>
               <p>Again, a <hi>Cast-Net</hi> is helpful for the taking small <hi>Fry,</hi> to feed <hi>Pikes</hi> in a Pond or the like, so that it may be necessary and beneficial many ways. Those that use it as destructively as they can imagine, will not revenge themselves much upon the <hi>Pikes;</hi> they may kill many small <hi>Jacks</hi> with it in shallow <hi>Streams,</hi> but the great <hi>Fish</hi> that lie deep and close, are too secure from the narrow compass of a <hi>Cast-Net:</hi> It may chance to fall upon a great one sometimes, yet if there be any <hi>Weeds</hi> or <hi>Fog</hi> in the place, and the <hi>Net</hi> be not strong and well bulleted, as also the Caster very wary in drawing it up, the <hi>Pike</hi> will deceive the expectations of the <hi>Fisher.</hi> In a clear place, where there are no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or obstructions, and the bottom smooth and level, it may haply enclose and draw up a good <hi>Pike;</hi> but where there are the least en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combrances to annoy the <hi>Net,</hi> it is to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, the <hi>Fish</hi> will make his escape: The new sort of <hi>Nets</hi> that are hung with Chains instead of Bullets, are too light for this service.</p>
               <p>Next to the <hi>Nets</hi> which kill by whole sale, the <hi>Trollers</hi> are often the greatest Enemies one to another, especially the way of the <hi>Ledger-Bait,</hi> which is very destructive to the Game, for that enticing way which they use with a live <hi>Bait,</hi> and laying such an Army of <hi>Hooks,</hi> must needs weaken the Forces of the Watry Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199384:46"/>
               <p>Dead <hi>Baits</hi> are not so pernicious, yet if they be too often used, they will much lessen the <hi>Fish;</hi> for at some seasons of the year they will bite almost till there is none left in the place: The way to favour it, is to be moderate, and not to beat a <hi>River</hi> too much or with too many <hi>Hooks;</hi> to <hi>Fish</hi> more for pleasure than for profit, and to come but once or twice in a Season to the same <hi>River.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Snare</hi> may do some harm at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the year in a Sunny day and a clear Water, that is only for by-places and narrow Scoures.</p>
               <p>One of the greatest Enemies is still to speak of, which must not be forgotten, because he is such a cunning and expert <hi>Fisher,</hi> that he generally preys upon only the greatest and the best <hi>Fish</hi> of all kinds. This is the <hi>Water-Dog,</hi> or <hi>Dog-Fisher,</hi> as some call him; which will walk five or ten Miles to a <hi>Pond</hi> in a Night, and some have disputed whether he be a Beast or a Fish: he can smell a <hi>Fish</hi> above an hundred yards from him, and then he devours them, and spoils more than he eats, leaving the Head and great part of the Back untouched. <hi>Gesner</hi> says, that his <hi>Stones</hi> are a good Remedy against the <hi>Falling Sickness;</hi> and that there is an Herb called <hi>Benione,</hi> which being hung in a Linnen Cloth near a <hi>Fish Pond</hi> or any haunt that he uses, it makes him to avoid the place. There is so many of them in a River in <hi>Cornwall,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:199384:47"/> that <hi>Camden</hi> says the Name of it is called <hi>Otter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey,</hi> from the abundance of <hi>Otters</hi> that there breed, and are fed in it. Though this amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious Creature be chief Regent, and is Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in the <hi>Waters,</hi> yet the greedy and audacious <hi>Pike,</hi> will sometimes set him at defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and is so bold as to give him Battel; as some have seen and observed it, that a <hi>Pike</hi> hath fought with an <hi>Otter</hi> for a <hi>Carp</hi> that he had gotten.</p>
               <p>It would not be amiss for the Conservation of the <hi>Waters,</hi> to keep the fence Months, which are three at the Spring in <hi>Spawning-time,</hi> for if the taking the <hi>Dam</hi> on her <hi>Nest</hi> when she hatches her young, were a sin so much against <hi>Nature,</hi> that it was forbidden in the Old Law, certainly the taking <hi>Fish</hi> in the time of their <hi>Spawning</hi> may be something unlawful as well as unnatural.</p>
               <p>Besides such unnatural <hi>Fishermen</hi> and all the Enemies before-mentioned, the <hi>Fish</hi> have many more, as the <hi>Bitterne,</hi> the <hi>Cormorant,</hi> the <hi>Osprey,</hi> the <hi>Sea-Gull,</hi> the <hi>Hern,</hi> the <hi>King-Fisher,</hi> and many others; which though they dare not make their prey upon the great <hi>Luce</hi> or <hi>Pike,</hi> yet they lessen the small <hi>Fry</hi> which should feed and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain the greater; and sometimes they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour young <hi>Jacks</hi> and <hi>Pickerils.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:199384:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> A Description of the <hi>Rivers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are in the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> 555 <hi>Rivers.</hi> I cannot conceive how the number jumps so equal, or comes to be so great; but that I suppose some small <hi>Brooks</hi> and <hi>Rivulets</hi> are taken in.</p>
               <p>Now of those 555, <hi>England</hi> alone claims the greatest share, having in it 325, though there may not be so many main Streams which either have the denomination, or the fulness and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of so vast a Current. As to their Diversities, is their Situations, their Distance and Remote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or their Nearness and Vicinity to the Sea; so they are different both in the qualities of their Water, as also their various kinds and species of <hi>Fishes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Those that have a more immediate intercourse with the Ocean, partake of its Influences, and have the same Vicissitudes, the same Fluxes, and Refluxes, the same Salt <hi>Water,</hi> and the same
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199384:48"/> Scaly Army attends them which rules and bears sway under <hi>Neptunes</hi> Government: These are too deep to be fathom'd by the short Cordage of a <hi>Line,</hi> and therefore cannot be brought within the compass of our designed Treatise. Those that are more in-land and farther distant from the common Receptacle of <hi>Waters,</hi> may be brought into the Lists, and fall under the Notion of our intended Subject.</p>
               <p>To begin then with the nearest, and to set forth the praises our Native Countrey, we may prefer the Neighbouring <hi>Avon,</hi> which hath afforded opportunities for our frequent Visits, and may challenge the greatest share of our own experience.</p>
               <p>This <hi>River</hi> consists chiefly of <hi>Pike</hi> and <hi>Perch,</hi> some good <hi>Bream,</hi> few <hi>Carpe, Chevins, Gudgeon, Roches,</hi> &amp;c. and very good <hi>Eel;</hi> it is a clear, fine <hi>Stream,</hi> in most places broad, and very deep. Some call it by the Name of <hi>Nine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it hath its Original from Nine <hi>Fountains,</hi> though I cannot discover above five Rivulets that flow in to the increasing of it: <hi>Springs</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are many, that joyn Forces to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it, the first of which arises about <hi>Daven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are several other <hi>Rivers</hi> that go by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199384:48"/> the Name of <hi>Avon,</hi> one of which takes its course through the middle of <hi>Warwick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next in order to <hi>Avon</hi> is <hi>Welland,</hi> which may claim the second place in our <hi>Description,</hi> having much encouraged our <hi>Diversions,</hi> and contributed very freely towards the perfecting and compleating of this Art.</p>
               <p>These two, like loving Sisters, meet and salute each other at <hi>Crowland,</hi> and then part again. The <hi>Welland</hi> cannot boast of that store and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Fish</hi> as her Neighbour <hi>Avon;</hi> with <hi>Pike</hi> and smaller <hi>Perch</hi> she is abundantly furnish'd, many <hi>Bream</hi> of a middle size, store of <hi>Chubs, Dace, Gudgeons, Eels,</hi> &amp;c. She hath many turns and windings in her Current, which makes her the more Commodious for <hi>Trolling,</hi> though slow in running; so that after a great Flood, there will be no <hi>Fishing</hi> for a long time.</p>
               <p>The Third, and next to these, is the <hi>Ouse</hi> in <hi>Bedfordshire,</hi> a fair <hi>River</hi> and full of <hi>Fish,</hi> much the same as that of <hi>Avon,</hi> a good <hi>Trolling River.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From thence to the famed <hi>Cham,</hi> which gives Name to our Mother <hi>Academia;</hi> for Historiaus and Antiquaries say, That by setting a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199384:49"/> Bridge over <hi>Cham,</hi> it was called <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>River</hi> is broad but shallow, and is not so Commodious for the <hi>Troll</hi> as the <hi>Cast-Net;</hi> here are many <hi>Gudgeons, Ruffs,</hi> small <hi>Jacks,</hi> some <hi>Trout</hi> and <hi>Chub;</hi> great part of it is <hi>Navigable;</hi> and therefore not so favourable for our <hi>Sport,</hi> not only because the sailing of the Vessels much disturbs and thickens the <hi>Waters</hi> with their Oars and Spreads, but because those continual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that keep the <hi>Water</hi> from settling, keep the <hi>Weeds</hi> from growing, which might harbour and shelter the <hi>Fish</hi> from the violence of <hi>Nets.</hi> The <hi>Stream</hi> of this <hi>Cham</hi> is somewhat Rapid and Velocious, both by reason of the shallowness of it, as also the level and streightness of it; it having but few Pits and Crooks which might render it serviceable for our <hi>Recreation.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if its <hi>Fountains</hi> cannot send forth such <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> that will multiply and generate <hi>Fishes</hi> to furnish the Adjacent Countries, yet from that ancient Scource of Liberal <hi>Arts</hi> and Pious <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature,</hi> have flowed full <hi>Streams</hi> of Learned Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which have refined all parts and corners of this Land.</p>
               <p>Next to this Seminary of good <hi>Education,</hi> may we place her Sister <hi>Oxonia</hi> the other Nurse and Breast of Learning: This, as well as the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199384:49"/> other, hath the denomination from the <hi>River</hi> the Foord of <hi>Oxen;</hi> or as some derive it <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, quasi Ouseford,</hi> from the River <hi>Ouse</hi> adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it.</p>
               <p>From thence we hasten to the River <hi>Swift,</hi> whether so called from the swiftness and velo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of its motion, is disputable; it waters and washeth <hi>Lutterworth</hi> in <hi>Leicester shire,</hi> and then kindly greets the greater <hi>Avon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The renowned <hi>Trent</hi> is generally known, being remarkable in the very Name and Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which some have it called from <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta,</hi> because it is stor'd with Thirty sorts of Fishes. If that be true, she must certainly bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row some of her Mothers Brood, the Salt Off-spring of the Sea; since there are not so many distinct kinds of <hi>Fishes</hi> that have their being and habitation in the Fresh <hi>Waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bordering to this, is the Capacious <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and many more spreading through the <hi>Northern Climate,</hi> the most Antient of which, is the greater <hi>Ouse,</hi> Commodious for Enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the City of <hi>York.</hi> Some say, <hi>Humber</hi> is not a distinct <hi>River</hi> of its self, but only the Mouth and <hi>Aestuarium</hi> of diverse <hi>Rivers</hi> here confluent and meeting together, as <hi>Youre, Darwent,</hi> especially <hi>Ouse</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> which there changeth its Name.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:199384:50"/>
               <p>More Northerly still is the noted <hi>Tweed,</hi> on whose <hi>Bank</hi> is seated the Impregnable Town of <hi>Berwick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The River <hi>Tine,</hi> so famous for <hi>New-Castle,</hi> and her Inexhaustible <hi>Coal Pits. Kent</hi> boasts much of her Princely <hi>Medway,</hi> famous for harbouring the Royal Navy.</p>
               <p>Swift-running <hi>Severne</hi> is a special Glory and Ornament to the Ciry <hi>Glocester,</hi> then which (says an Ancient Author) there is not any for <hi>Channel</hi> broader, for <hi>Stream</hi> swifter, or for <hi>Fish</hi> better stored. There is in it a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rage and fury of <hi>Waters,</hi> which may be called a <hi>Gulph</hi> or <hi>Whirl-pool</hi> of <hi>Waves,</hi> raising up the Sand from the bottom, winding and driving upon great heaps; sometimes she over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floweth her Banks, and roveth a great way up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of her Bordering grounds, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain retireth as Conqueror into her usual <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels;</hi> unhappy is the Vessel which she taketh full upon the sides; for if the <hi>VVatermen</hi> are aware of it, they turn the Vessel upon it, and cut through the middest of it, whereby they check, and avoid that violence and danger: she is called <hi>Sabrina,</hi> from the name of a Maid that was there drowned.</p>
               <p>There are many noted <hi>Rivers</hi> in <hi>Darbyshire,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199384:50"/> Lancashire, Devonshire, Shropshire,</hi> &amp;c. the Description of which would be fit for a larger Volum, and cannot be reduced into this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitome.</p>
               <p>The most considerable of them all may be summ'd up, and comprehended in these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Verses.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Queen</hi> Thames <hi>the First, for Ships and Swans is Crown'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Chrystal</hi> Trent <hi>for Fords and Fish Renown'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Stately</hi> Severn <hi>for her Shore is prais'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Newcastle<hi>'s</hi> Tine <hi>to</hi> Albion<hi>'s Cliffs is rais'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>West Chester <hi>brags much of her holy</hi> Dee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The</hi> Peake <hi>her</hi> Dove, <hi>whose Banks so fertile be.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>York <hi>many wonders of her</hi> Ouse <hi>can tell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Kent <hi>will say her</hi> Medway <hi>doth excell.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cotswoll <hi>commends her</hi> Isis <hi>to the</hi> Tame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our Western parts extol the</hi> Avon<hi>'s Fame.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:199384:51"/>
                  <l>The Northern Borders boasts of <hi>Tweed</hi>'s fair flood,</l>
                  <l>And the old <hi>Lee</hi> brags of <hi>Danish</hi> blood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Receipt to dress a <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke your <hi>Pike,</hi> and open him, rub him within with Salt and Claret Wine, save the Milt, a little of the Blood and Fat; cut him in two or three pieces and put him in when the Water Boils; put in with him sweet Marjorum, Savory, Time or Fennel, with a good handful of Salt; let him boil near half an hour: For the Sauce, take sweet Butter, Anchovies, Horse Raddish, Claret Wine, of each a good quantity; a little of the Blood, Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte, or Garlick; some Lemon sliced, beat them well together, and serve him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:51"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS of the BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> OF the Name and Nature of a <hi>Pike, Page. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> Of the Parts and Lineaments of a <hi>Pike, Page. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> Of the Age and growth of a <hi>Pike, Page. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Of the Seat and Harbour of a <hi>Pike, Page. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> Of the best Seasons for Trolling, <hi>Page. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Of the Feed of a <hi>Pike,</hi> and when he is fattest, <hi>Page. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VII.</hi> Of the Baits for <hi>Trolling, Page. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> Of the <hi>Pouch-Hook, Page. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. IX.</hi> Of the <hi>Trolling Line, Page. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. X.</hi> Of the <hi>Pole, Page. 46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> How to Bait the <hi>Hook,</hi> and to play the <hi>Bait, Page. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> How to strike a <hi>Pike</hi> and land him, <hi>Page. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIII.</hi> How to preserve a River for <hi>Trolling, Page. 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XIV.</hi> A Description of the <hi>Rivers, Page. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Receipt to dress a <hi>Pike, Page. 78.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:52"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and sold by <hi>Thomas Helder</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Little Britain:</hi> 1682.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DAretis Phrygii, Historicorum omnium primi, de Bello Trojano, Libri Sex. Latino Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine á</hi> Josepho Exoniensi <hi>Elegantissime redditi.</hi> 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Seu Tractatus de Tonis in Lingua Graecanica: Scriptus per</hi> R. F. <hi>in</hi> S. T. B. 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
            </p>
            <p>A Good help for Weak Memories, or the Contents of every Chapter in the Bible, in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetical Dysticks: Being very profitable for such as desire to repeat Books, or find out divers places in the Scriptures, especially in the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Books. 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ENCHIRIDION,</hi> Containing Institutions Divine: Contemplative, Practical. Moral: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thical, Oeconomical, Political. By <hi>Fra. Quarles.</hi> 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miscellanea,</hi> Or a mixture of Choice Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and Institutions <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Divine:</hi> Composed for private use. By <hi>J. H.</hi> 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ludus Mathematicus,</hi> Or the Mathematical Game: Explaining the Description, Constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Use of the Numerical Table of Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By <hi>E. W.</hi> 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:53"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199384:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>